<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rules, orders and instructions, made and published by the commissioners of customs and excize in Scotland, to be observed by the several officers conjunctly of both, in relation as well to customs as excize of forreign goods upon importation or sale</title>
            <title>Rules, etc.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Commissioners of Excise.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830079</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830079</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57889)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2018:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rules, orders and instructions, made and published by the commissioners of customs and excize in Scotland, to be observed by the several officers conjunctly of both, in relation as well to customs as excize of forreign goods upon importation or sale</title>
                  <title>Rules, etc.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Commissioners of Excise.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Commissioners of Customs.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Christopher Higgins, in Harts-Close, over against the Trone-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Commissioners of Excise --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland. --  Commissioners of Customs --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RULES, ORDERS AND INSTRUCTIONS, Made and Publiſhed by the COMMISSIONERS OF CUSTOMS and EXCIZE IN <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> To be obſerved by the ſeveral Officers conjunctly of both, in relation as well to Cuſtoms as Excize of Forreign Goods upon Importation or Sale.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by <hi>Chriſtopher Higgins,</hi> in <hi>Hartſ-Cloſe,</hi> over againſt the Trone-Church, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34528:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34528:2"/>
            <head>BY THE COMMISSIONERS OF CUSTOMS and EXCIZE In <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as his Highneſs Council in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for the Government thereof, have been pleaſed for the moſt benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Publick eaſe and commodity of Merchants, and other Traders and Dealers, to entruſt the buſineſſe of Cuſtoms and Excize to the care and management of one and the ſame Commiſsioners, with Power to collect, levie, receive and take both the ſaid Duties, according to the Rules of them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively impoſed and ſetled to be received for th ſame in <hi>England,</hi> by Act, Ordinance, Order or Declaration, as well of his Highneſſe as of Parliament in that behalf. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the ſaid Rules are many and various, and which, (if neglected or omitted to be practiſed and put in execution) may prove very prejudicial to the Commonwealth, as well in the matter of Customs and Excize, as by the Importing and Exporting of Prohibited Goods and Merchandize. For Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy whereof, and to the end the ſeveral Collectors and other Officers imployed in and about the ſame, may more fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34528:3"/>the reſpective Duties of their Places, and obſerve and keep an Uniformity of Actings and Proceedings in the due and regular mannagement of Affairs of the Cuſtoms and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize reſpectively; And that none may pretend ignorance, The preſent Commiſsioners of Cuſtoms and Excize in <hi>Scotland,</hi> aſwell for the Reaſons aforeſaid, and out of their fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire faithfully to diſcharge the great Truſt incumbent on them, as the tender regard they have in themſelves of hindering any perſons whatſoever ignorantly or unwittingly to commit any Offences in breach of the Laws, Have therefore, not only from the ſeveral Laws now in force in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> made, drawn, framed and publiſhed ſuch <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to the ſeveral Officers employed in the ſeveral Ports, (as are moſt ſuitable to the juncture of things in this Nation; And which therefore the ſeveral and reſpective Officers are hereby ordered and required to obſerve, perform, fulfill and keep) but have alſo made collection of the ſeveral <hi>Fines, Penalties</hi> and <hi>Forfeitures</hi> deviſed and made by the ſaid Laws, that ſo thoſe whom their affection to their Country and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth cannot reſtrain from uſing indirect practiſes in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Publick Revenue thereof, may be contained within due bounds, from the fence they may have of the ſeverity of the Law, which they will draw upon themſelves if they ſhall nevertheleſs continue wilfully to infringe and break the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated at <hi>LEITH</hi> 
                  <date>the firſt day of <hi>September,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and fifty ſix.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Ja. Mac-Dowal, Leo. Lytcot, Edm. Syler, Tho. Tucker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34528:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS,</hi> For the ſeverall <hi>COLLECTORS</hi> of <hi>CUSTOMS</hi> in the Ports of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> as to Goods Inward and Outwards, from, or for beyond the Seas.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collectors du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attend at the Head Port.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE COLLECTORS</hi> of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall and reſpective Ports of this Nation, are duly and conſtantly from time to time by themſelves, or ſome other (for whom they will be anſwerable, when, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they ſhall have leave, or may other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be neceſſitated to abſent themſelves) to give their diligent and conſtant attendance, at the hours, times and places appointed at the Cuſtom-Houſe of the Chief or Head Port of his Diſtrict. And becauſe in many the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Ports, the Merchants by reaſon of diſtance of Place, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly make their Entries at the Chief or Head Port; The Collector is by Commiſſion under his Hand and Seal,<note place="margin">To commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion one of his Waiters in a Member Port</note> to appoint one of the Waiters of his Port (which he in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall conceive to be moſt fit and apt for ſuch a work, and for whom he ſhall be reſponſible) to attend and officiate in ſuch Member-Port of his Diſtrict in every thing, <hi>mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis</hi> as a Collecto, but ſo far onely, and no further than the Collector ſhall by ſuch Commiſſion particularly direct and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34528:4"/>appoint, and all as ſhall be for the moſt eaſe and diſpatch of the Merchant, benefit and advantage of the Publick: And the Name of ſuch Waiter as he ſhall appoint, he is from time to time to tranſmit to the Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Caſh or Day and Ship-Books.</note>
               <hi>Every</hi> Collector for the better carrying on and managing the affair wherein he is intruſted, as to Subſidy and Cuſtoms, ſhall cauſe four ſeverall fair Books to be prepared, One of which is to be imployed and kept for a Caſh or Day Book, of all Moneys received for Cuſtoms Inwards or Outwards, and two other of them for Ship Books, Inwards and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collectors to appoint Waiters to attend the landing of Goods.</note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> the arrivall of any Ship in any Port, the Collector and chief Searcher in ſuch Ports where any ſuch Searcher is appointed, or elſe the Collector alone is to nominate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect by Warrant under their or his hand, one or more of the Watters (appointed to attend in that Fort, or any other Port or Place of his Precinct or Diſtrict) to take charge of ſuch Ships, and to ſee the Goods and Merchandizes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in laden, cleared and diſcharged, according to ſuch Warrant as he or they ſhall receive from the Collector and Cheque joyntly, of the ſaid Port where the ſame ſhall happen to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and unladen:<note place="margin">But the Maſter is firſt to enter his Ship. and make report upon Oath.</note> But no ſuch Warrant is to be granted or iſſued before ſuch time as the Maſter or Purſer coming by way of Merchandize, or with Commodities from any Port, ſhall not onely enter openly in the Cuſtome-houſe, the name of the Ship, and of the Maſter, the Burden, of whence, and from what Place ſhe is fraighted; but alſo deliver under his hand, and upon his Oath unto the Collector and Cheque, a Bill of the Particulars and Contents of the whole Lading of the Ship, with the Names of the ſeverall Merchants, and the Marks, Package, and outward form or Bulk of the Goods and Merchandizes according to his knowledge: And ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make Declaration upon Oath, that he hath not broken Bulk ſince he came into the Port, nor to any other Port of this Nation, otherwayes than in the ſaid Bill ſhall be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſhall anſwer to all ſuch other Queſtions, concerning the direct Quantity of Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid Ship, as ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34528:4"/>be demanded of him by the Collector and Cheque. And in caſe it ſhall happen, that he hath broken Bulk, either in that or in any other Port; then he ſhall alſo deliver upon his Oath, the particulars of the ſaid Goods ſo delivered in the Port or Ports where he brake Bulk.</p>
            <p>Which Ent y and Declaration made, as aforeſaid, ſhall be entred in words at length into the Ship-Book Inwards,<note place="margin">The ſame to be entred in the Ship-Book.</note> after the Ships Entry, and afterwards (having a <hi>Memorandum</hi> indorſed thereupon of ſuch Oath) ſhall be numbred and filed in its due place and order, and together with the Ship-Book, (who is in like ſort and manner to be numbred in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent) ſhall be ſafely kept in the Cuſtom-houſe for a Record thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Maſters</hi> or Purſers of Ships,<note place="margin">Maſters and Purſers when to enter and unlade.</note> arriving from any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts, ſhall within four dayes after their arrivall, make Entry of their Ship or Veſſell, as aforeſaid, and ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade and diſcharge the ſame, or ſo much thereof as is intended to be unladen and diſcharged with all convenient ſpeed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Merchants entring to give three Bills.</note>
               <hi>Every Merchant</hi> or other perſon entring Goods or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities Inwards, ſhall make Entry of the ſame particularly, by delivering three Bills thereof at large (two of which are to be ſigned by his own hand, or the hand of his Aſſigns) to the Collector and Cheque, mentioning and expreſſing the Name of the Ship, and of the Maſter, of whence, and from what place it was fraighted, with the Marks and Numbers of the Fardells, Bulk and Package in the Margent, and the true Quantities and Qualities of the Goods therein contained and expreſſed in words at length, and not in Figures: As alſo, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Merchant be a Native, or a Merchant Stranger, in manner and form following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <note place="margin">Form of the Merchants Entry.</note>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Leith</hi> Cuſtoms. In the <hi>Hopewel</hi> of <hi>Amſterd. Jo. Johnſon</hi> Mr. from <hi>Middleb.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Taylar Ind.</hi> or <hi>Alien,</hi> if the Maſter be a Stranger.</p>
                  <p>Five Barrells of Soap.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And the ſaid Collector and Cheque, having diſtinctly and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34528:5"/>ſeverally caſt up,<note place="margin">The Cuſtoms to be caſt up on the Bills.</note> with all convenient ſpeed, the value of the Goods and Merchandize therein mentioned, according to the Book of Rates (or otherwiſe if not therein rated, as is by the ſaid Book, or any other Act or Ordinance directed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) ſhall either of them upon one of the ſaid Bills write the Cuſtom and Subſidy due thereupon, and having ſigned, numbred, and dated the ſame according to its order and day of Entry, ſhall reciprocally deliver unto each other the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Bill (which each of them had reſpectively caſt up,<note place="margin">One of them to remain with the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, the other with the Cheque.</note> ſigned and entred) to remain and lye, <hi>viz.</hi> The Collectors Bill with the Cheque, and the Chequ's Bill with the Collector, for an originall Bill, or voucher of Entry; which ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at leaſt ſome time the ſame day, together with the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy and Cuſtoms thereupon due and received, be entered and charged by the Collector to Accompt in the Column of his Caſh or Day Book, appointed for Receipts of Cuſtoms, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which the third Bill being Subſcribed both by the Collector and Cheque (and numbered and dated,<note place="margin">And the third to be the Waiters Warrant.</note> as the former) ſhall be ſufficient warrant to the Waitors unto whom the ſame ſhall preſently be directed, to ſuffer and permit the Wares and Merchandizes therein mentioned to be landed and diſcharged accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poſt-entries, when and how to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note>
               <hi>In caſe</hi> of ſhort Entry made of any Goods Inwards, wherein upon examination to be taken before the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners or Collectors for Cuſtoms, it ſhall appear that the Merchant had no intention of fraud to the Commonwealth, and the Goods un-entered ſhall not exceed twenty <hi>per cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in the quantity thereof in proportion with the Goods mentioned in the Warrant, (whereof the Five <hi>per centum</hi> is to be accompted part) the Merchant ſhall be admitted to mend his Entry without Seizure; But this Liberty is not to extend,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To any Entries of Goods paſſing Outwards in any caſe whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Nor to any Goods entered Inwards, which ſhall be landed at unlawful time or place, or in the abſence of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the Cuſtoms properly concerned therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34528:5"/> 3. <hi>Nor in any Caſes where upon Examination, intention of fraud to the Commonwealth ſhall be diſcovered, or the Goods landed, and not entred, ſhall exceed the quantity above-written. For in all ſuch Caſes it is expected and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that Seizures be duly made and proſecuted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the duties of the Officers, and the Laws in that behalf eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods at ſight how to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up.</note>
               <hi>All manner</hi> of Wares and Merchandize, that for ſome juſt cauſe or other (firſt allowed of, and admitted by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners themſelves in the Port of <hi>Leith,</hi> and in all other Ports by the Collector and Cheque) any Merchant may happen to enter at ſight, ſhall be taken up by a Warrant for view, dated the day of the Entry thereof, ſubſcribed by the Commiſſioners themſelves, or Collector and Cheque, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and delivered unto the chief Searcher, or other Waiter or Waiters (where there is no ſuch Searcher) who ſhall ſee the ſame forthwith brought unto the Cuſtome-houſe Key or VVharf, and give knowledge thereof unto the Collector and Cheque, who ſhall preſently cauſe the ſame to be ſearched, viewed, weighed, meaſured, or otherwayes as the nature of the Commodity ſhall require in ſome convenient place. And the Owner or Proprietor ſhall forthwith after that, make an Entry thereof particularly under his hand, or the hand of his Aſſign, with the Collector and Cheque, and thereupon war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to be made for the clearing and paſſing the VVares and Merchandize, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bills of Store or Portage.</note>
               <hi>No Bills</hi> of Store or Portage ſhall be granted unto any Mariners or Seamen, at their coming in, or going out, or any others for damage goods, Miſ-Entries, or Over-Entries, but by ſpeciall Order from the Commiſſioners; which Bills ſo granted, aſwell as Cocquets and other Warrants, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to ſome Waiter, and not the Perſon to whom granted, and the ſame to be void, unleſſe ſerved on ſuch day, or within ſo many dayes as ſhall be therein limited and appointed; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall thoſe Bills be ſerved upon any Goods of any Perſon whatſoever, other than the Perſon to whom they ſhall be granted; or out of, or upon any other Ship or Ships, than
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34528:6"/>what are, or ſhal be mentioned in the ſaid Bils, without the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial directions &amp; appointment of the Commiſſioners therein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All Warrants to be paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in the Cuſtomhouſe.</note>
               <hi>No Entry</hi> or agreement with any Merchant, or others, for Cuſtom or Subſidy Inwards or Outwards, ſhall be made by the Collector, or other, nor any Cocquet, Warrant, or Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat ſealed or ſubſcribed, but openly in the Cuſtom-houſe, by the Collector and Cheque; And every Merchant ſhall paſte his particular Cocquet, Warrant or Certificat, the ſame day he entreth his Goods.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maſters, Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, entring Outwards.</note>
               <hi>Every Maſter,</hi> Shipper, Purſer, or other taking charge of a Voyage, that ſhall lade any Goods or Merchandizes for the Parts beyond the Seas, ſhall by Entry under his hand, ſignifie unto the Collector of the Port where he ladeth (that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to lade, and to what place) before he receive or take into his Ship, any Goods or Merchandize, and before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, ſhall give notice of his whole Lading,<note place="margin">To give a particular of his Lading, and anſwer upon his oath.</note> with the names of the Merchants, and other Perſons that have laden Goods with him, or in his Bottom; And further, truly ſhal anſwer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, to all ſuch queſtions as ſhall be demanded of him by the Collector and Cheque of the Port where he ſhall ſo Lade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collector to appoint Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Ships.</note>
               <hi>After the</hi> Entry of any Ships, as aforeſaid, the Collector and chief Searcher, where ſuch Searcher is appointed, and in all other Ports, the Collector alone ſhall by Warrant under their or his hand, direct one or more Waiters of the ſame Port, to take charge of ſuch Ship, and ſee the Goods and Merchandize therein, to be ſhipped, laden, and put on Board, according to ſuch Warrant as ſhall be given by the Collector and Cheque joyntly for doing thereof. And when, and as often as any Trade more than ordinary ſhall chance to happen in any Head Port, or Member thereof, ſo as the Waiters appointed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in thoſe places,<note place="margin">Incaſe of Trade more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, how to ſend for help.</note> cannot poſſibly be able to ſee unto the Lading or unlading of the Goods and Merchandizes which ſhall be ſhipped out, or brought in. Every Collector of ſuch Head Port (if the ſuddenneſſe of the thing will not give him time or liberty to advertiſe the Commiſſioners thereof, for ſome other or more Waiters to be ſent from <hi>Leith</hi> to his help or aſſiſtance) ſhall incaſe his Port lye Northerly, ſend unto
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34528:6"/>the Collector of the next Port lying Southerly, for one or more Waiters, who ſhall thereupon ſend ſuch unto him: and that Collector at the ſame time (if the occaſions of his Port re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it) ſhall in like manner ſend to the next Port adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Southerly of his Port; and ſo from Port to Port, untill at length the want or deficiency of Waiters in the laſt Port, may be ſupplied from <hi>Leith.</hi> As for the Ports lying Weſterly, they are to be ſupplied, as aforeſaid, by ſending ſtill unto the Collector of the next Port adjoyning to them Eaſterly; and ſo from Port to Port (if neceſſity require) as aforeſaid. But if the ſame may at any time be done and performed aſwell, and with leſſe charge, by entertainment of ſome faithfull perſon, to officiate in extraordinary, during the emergency of things, it is left to the diſcretion of the Collector to entertain ſuch perſon, or elſe to ſend for help, as aforeſaid, according as he in his judgment ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Merchants Entryes Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, how to be made.</note>
               <hi>Every Merchant,</hi> or other, that will tranſport or ſhip out any Goods by way of Merchandize for forreign parts, ſhall make his Entry particularly thereof, with the Collector and Cheque, by three Bills under his hand, or the hand of his Aſſigns, with the Name of the Ship, the Maſter, the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, of whence, and to what place it is fraighted, with the Marks and Numbers of the Packs, Cask, Fardells, or other outward Form or Bulk, and the true quantity and quality of the Goods therein contained, in words at length, which ſhall be ſigned and entred, filed,<note place="margin">Filed and kept.</note> and kept by the Collector and Cheque reſpectively, as in the caſe of Entries Inwards, and the Moneys due, and received for Subſidy and Cuſtomes by the Collector, charged unto Account in like manner accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by their true denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Eſpeciall care</hi> is to be had and taken, that all Goods, Wares and Merchandizes Inwards and Outwards, be entred in their own true denomination, according to their proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, quality, ſortment, ſpecies and kind, by which they are commonly and uſually known and diſtinguiſhed, and according to their ſeveral terms and appellations given, and in ſuch ſort as the ſame are mentioned and directed in the Book of Rates to pay, whether by Groſs weight, Number, Meaſure, Dozen, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34528:7"/>otherways.<note place="margin">Goods to be entred in the Merchants own name,</note> And further, that no manner of Goods or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, coming in, or going out, be entred in any other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or Merchants name, ſave in the name onely of the true Merchant, Owner or Proprietor of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods entred in one Veſſel, and ſhipt in another.</note>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> and Merchandize Cuſtomed Outwards upon any Ship or Veſſell, which for ſome cauſe or other, cannot be laden on Board the ſame Ship, ſhall be appointed to another Ship by Certificat, openly ſubſcribed and delivered in the Cuſtom-houſe upon the Oaths of the chief Searcher (where ſuch Searcher is appointed) and the Waiter, or one of them, and of the Owners and Proprietors of the ſaid Goods and Merchandize openly taken, that the ſaid Goods did not paſs according to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Cocquet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Store and Portage, how to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</note>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> and Merchandize allowed for Store, Portage, or other cauſe whatſoever, ſhall duly and daily be entred in the Caſh or Day-book, in the ſame Order as they are paſſed; and although they pay neither Cuſtoms nor Subſidy, ſhall never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe be valued and rated as they ſhould have been, had they not been paſſed by Stores; but ſhall and may be omitted to be drawn out; or put into the Columne for Receipt of Cuſtoms, or added up in the Account of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Officer whatſoever to take any Fees.</note>
               <hi>No Collector,</hi> Searcher, VVaiter, or other Officer whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, imployed in, or about the buſineſſe of the Cuſtoms, ſhall either directly or indirectly, demand, take, or receive from the Merchant, or any other perſon whatſoever, any Moneys by way of Fee or Gratuity, for, or in reſpect of any Certificat, Bill, Cocquet, Tranſire, Ticket, Sufferance, Bond, or any other thing whatſoever,<note place="margin">Except for Skippers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Bills of Entryes.</note> to be by him or them done or performed as Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, Searcher, or VVaiter. And in caſe any of them ſhall at any time, at the inſtance and requeſt of any Skipper or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, make or write any report or Bill of content of any Ship, or Bills of Entry, Inwards or Outwards, no Officer making ſuch Bills,<note place="margin">Report 1d. Each Bill of Entry <hi>ob.</hi>
               </note> ſhall demand, take, or receive more than one penny for writing the Skippers; and no more than an half penny a Bill for writing Bills of Entryes for the Merchant, upon pain of being diſmiſſed from his or their imployment, who ſhall do contrary thereunto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34528:7"/>
            <head>INSTRUCTIONS for the COLLECTORS as to the Coaſt-Buſineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He buſineſſe of the Coaſt</hi> (which is to be underſtood only of Goods going, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to, or from any the Ports of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi>) being ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the reſt, and therefore to be kept in a different way and manner, and diſtinctly by it ſelf. The Collector is here, and in this Affair, to make,<note place="margin">The Coaſt-Book.</note> or cauſe a fair Book to be prepared and kept, by the name of the <hi>Coaſt Book;</hi> In which all Coaſt Cocquets, Tranſires, and Certificates thereupon are from time to time to be duly entred the ſame day, and in the ſame order as they are preſented and paſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Coaſt Goods are to be entred.</note>
               <hi>This Coaſt Book</hi> is to be ruled with a double Margent, the one to the right hand, and the other to the left hand, on each ſide. On the left Page of this Book all Cocquets and Tranſires Outwards are to be entred,<note place="margin">Outwards.</note> placing the Name of the Port for which any Goods ſhall be ſhipped, in the Margent on the left; and the date of the Certificate, or Return from the Port where they were landed, on the right ſide of the ſaid Page.<note place="margin">Inwards.</note> On the right Page all Cocquets and Tranſires for Goods Inwards from the Coaſt, are to be entred; and in the Margent of the left ſide, the Name of the Port from whence the Goods came is to be expreſſed; and on the other ſide, the date of the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Certificate, or Return of the landing of the ſaid Goods: But in the middle of both Pages, between the Margents on either ſides, the Quantity and Quality of all Goods from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34528:8"/>Coaſt, Outwards or Inwards, reſpectively, is to be moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly entred, with the date of the reſpective Cocquets and Tranſires, by which the ſame Goods have been paſſed, either Outwards or Inwards; The form of which Book, with the Coaſt Cocquet Certificate followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The Form of the Coaſt-Book.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">OUTWARDS.</cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">INVVARDS.</cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>24. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1655</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>26. <hi>June,</hi> 1655</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>London</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>James Ramſey Ind.</hi> five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred quarters of Oats in the <hi>Hannab</hi> of <hi>Leith, John Taylor</hi> Mr.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cert.</hi> 16. <hi>June,</hi> 1656.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>New-Caſtle.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>John Booth Ind.</hi> two hundred undreſt Hides in the <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of <hi>Kirkal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Tho. White</hi> Mr. Dated 24. <hi>December,</hi> 1655</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cert.</hi> 29. <hi>June,</hi> 1656.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of a Coaſt-Cocquet.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>KNow ye that <hi>James Ramſey</hi> Ind. bath Laden in this Port five hundred Quarters of Oats in the <hi>Hannah</hi> of <hi>Leith, John Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> Maſter, for <hi>London,</hi> ſecurity being given. Dated the four and twentieth day of <hi>November, 1655.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of a Tranſire for the Coaſt.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>KNow ye that <hi>Alexander Farquhar Ind.</hi> is permitted to paſſe fourty Barrels of Figs, qt. thirty hundred wt. in the <hi>Hopewell</hi> of <hi>Brunt-Iſland, Patrick Angus</hi> Maſter, for <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> Dated the ſecond of <hi>December, 1655.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34528:8"/>
                  <head>The Form of a Certificate.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>LEITH.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>KNow ye that <hi>John Booth Ind.</hi> hath diſcharged and put on ſhore in this Port two hundred undreſt Hides, out of the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>Kirkaldy, Tho. White</hi> Maſter, from <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> ſecurity being given, as <hi>per</hi> Cocquet, dated the five and twentieth day of <hi>November</hi> laſt: Witneſſe the Seal of our Office this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of March, <hi>1656.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>EVery Merchant, or other perſon,<note place="margin">Merchants entring Goods for the Coaſt, to give Bond.</note> intending to ſhip or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any Goods or Merchandize (prohibited tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or carrying beyond the Seas) to diſcharge or unlade the ſame in any other Port or place of <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> ſhall before the ſhipping thereof, declare and manifeſt under his or their Hands, by Bill of Entry (as in all other Caſes) to the Collector and Cheque of the Cuſtoms in the Port where the ſame ſhall be ſhipped, the Meaſure, Length, Number, and other Contents and Value of ſuch Goods, together with the Name of the Ship, and of the Maſter, the Place of whence, and for which he is fraighted; and with the approbation of the ſaid Collector and Cheque, ſhall alſo make and enter into a ſufficient Obligation, according to the Law of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in which he ſhall be bound with ſufficient Sureties, or Caution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in ſuch ſums of Money as ſhall amount to double the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Goods ſo declared and manifeſted, with Condition that the ſame ſhall be diſcharged at ſome Port within <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> (where ſuch Goods may be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thither) and in no other place whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To return Certificate within four moneths.</note>
               <hi>Every Perſon</hi> giving Bond and Security, as aforeſaid, is within four moneths (at furtheſt) after ſhipping of his Goods, to bring a true Certificate from the Port or place where he or they ſhall diſcharge the ſaid Goods, teſtifying the ſaid Goods ſo ſhipped, and the true Nature, Length, Weight, Number, and other Contents or Value thereof, to be there diſcharged: Which Certificate, upon the diſcharge of the Goods in any Port in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be delivered to the party delivering and diſcharging the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34528:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be taken upon ſhipping woollen Yarn, Flocks, Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fells, Earth and Clay.</note>
               <hi>If any perſon or perſon</hi> ſhall ſhip out any woollen Yarn, woollen Flocks, Wool-fels, Earth or Clay, the Collector ſhall take double Security (over and above double the value) for three ſhillings for every pound thereof, with Condition, That the ſame ſhall be landed in ſome Port of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as is directed by Law, and according to the tenour of the uſual Coaſt Bonds.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All Bonds to be returned to the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners.</note>
               <hi>All ſuch,</hi> or any other Bonds already taken by any the Collectors, are with all convenient ſpeed, and all ſuch other Bonds whatſoever in the future to be taken by any the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, are, and ſhall be monethly returned up and delivered to the Commiſſioners at the Cuſtom-houſe in <hi>Leith,</hi> that ſuch proceſſe and other proceedings may be had thereupon, as of right belongeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Goods to be ſhipped without ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>france, Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</note>
               <hi>The Collector</hi> in every Port is to take care that no Goods whatſoever be ſhipped from Port to Port, before a Sufferance be paſſed for the ſame; nor any Native Commodities or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures made thereof be tranſported, before a Cocquet be paſt, and good Security given for landing the ſame at ſome other Port or place of this Nation, or of <hi>England,</hi> or elſe <hi>Ireland</hi> (if ſuch Goods may be ſhipped thither) as is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Law, nor any forreign Goods, before a Tranſire be paſt for the ſame: And if any Goods ſhall be ſhipped contrary hereunto, or that any Goods ſhall be brought in from one Port to another, or ſhall be landed or found on board any Ship whether landed or not landed, for which there is no Cocquet or Tranſire, or being more in quantity than is in the Cocquet or Tranſire therein mentioned,<note place="margin">If ſo, to be ſeized.</note> that in ſuch caſes, Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure be made, and notice thereof given to the Commiſſioners, and ſo to provide that the ſame, or any part thereof, be not diſcharged, without order of the Commiſſioners firſt had and given therein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maſters and Purſers how to enter for the Coaſt.</note>
               <hi>Before</hi> the going out of, or upon coming into Port of any Ship or Veſſel, for, unto, or from any other Port or place of <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> the Maſter or Purſer of every ſuch Ship is to make Entry of his Ship, and the reſpective Merchants, Proprietors and Owners, are to make Entry of their Goods,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34528:9"/>Merchandize and Commodities, as is required to be made and done for all Ships, Goods and Merchandize Outwards or Inwards, for, or from any forreign Parts beyond the Seas;<note place="margin">How Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhall enter.</note> But any Merchant or other, intending to lade or ſhip, and ſo making Entry of any Goods Outwards for the Coaſt, the Collector and Cheque are thereupon to make a Cocquet or Tranſire, at the nature of his Entry ſhall require;<note place="margin">Their Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets and Tranſires to remain in the cuſtody of the Collector and Cheque.</note> Which Cocquet or Tranſire, is to remain in the joynt Cuſtody of the ſaid Collector and Cheque, untill ſuch time as the Merchant is, or ſhall be ready to carry or ſhip his Goods on Board, and then upon notice given thereof, to be delivered to the Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appointed to attend that Ship in which they are to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, who ſhall forthwith ſee the ſame done. And if the Merchant have not before,<note place="margin">Till the Goods ſhall be ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and then to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Waiter to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſe.</note> he ſhall then give the Marks and Numbers of his Goods, which ſhall be indorſed on the ſaid Cocquet or Tranſire, and the Waiter alſo ſhall write his name thereupon, with the time when he ſaw the ſame ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and preſently after, ſhall deliver the ſame back unto the chief Searcher, or elſe unto the Collector, where there is no chief Searcher who ſhall keep the ſame by him, till the Ship be fully laden,<note place="margin">By him to the Searcher or Collector. Who after ful lading and oath given by the Maſter, &amp; ſearch made, Shal deliver the ſame, or elſe one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Cocquet to ſuch Maſter No Ships un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lading, to be d ſcharged before exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, &amp; ſearch of the ſame.</note> and then the Maſter or Purſer thereof coming and making Declaration upon Oath, that he hath received no Goods on Board, but what have been laden by Cocquet, Tranſire, or Sufferance; and the ſaid Searcher or Collector, or ſome Waiter appointed by him, going on Board to ſearch, and finding no other, or more Goods laden therein, then for which there was, or had been Cocquet, Tranſire, or Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance granted for doing thereof, ſhall thereupon deliver the Cocquets and Tranſires remaining in his cuſtody, or elſe one general Cocquet for all, unto the Maſter or Purſer of the Ship, who is to be cleared and diſcharged, that She may proceed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Her Voyage accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Ships</hi> Inwards from the Coaſt, are to be diſcharged, or ſuffered to depart from the Key, or have any Goods <hi>de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo</hi> put on Board, before ſuch time as the chief Searcher, or Collector where there is no chief Searcher, ſhall firſt have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the particular Entryes with the Maſters or Purſers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34528:10"/>Entry, and finding the ſame to agree, ſhall afterwards go on Board, and ſee that there are no Goods left remaining on Board; but that the whole Lading hath been really and truly delivered and diſcharged; The ſame <hi>mutaris mutandis</hi> to be obſerved for, and upon all Ships Inwards from beyond the Seas.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In paſſing</hi> of Goods from Port to Port, the Collectors and other Officers,<note place="margin">What to be underſtood by Goods Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomable.</note> are to underſtand by Goods Cuſtomable, All Wares and Commodities growing, wrought or manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured within this Nation, and all forreign Commodities and Merchandizes which have been imported and remained in this Nation, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by an Engliſh-man above twelve Months, and by a Stranger above nine Months, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty altered by the ſale thereof made by the firſt Importer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34528:10"/>
            <head>INSTRUCTIONS <hi>For the</hi> COLLECTORS, <hi>in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of</hi> SUBSIDY <hi>and</hi> CUSTOMS.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collector to receive accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the book of Rates, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Collector</hi> in every Port, appointed for receiving of Subſidy and Cuſtoms up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Goods, Wares and Merchandize, Imported into, and Exported out of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are faithfully to obſerve, do and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame, according to the Articles, Rules and Directions of the preſent Book of Rates, and ſuch others as are directed to be received for, or concerning the payment of the Subſidy of Tunnage and Poundage, or the Importation, or Exportation, or Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Goods prohibited by any Statute, Act or Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, Ordinance or Order of his Highneſs the Lord Protector and his Councill, now in force in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and become ſo in <hi>Scotland</hi> by the Union of both Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; And to proceed in all things belonging to the duty of his Place, according to the ſame, and according to ſuch Rules and Inſtructions as he ſhall from time to time receive or have from the chief Commiſſioners in that behalf.<note place="margin">What Wine are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of the growth of the Levant. What natives and ſtrangers ſhall pay.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Collector</hi> is to take notice, That all Wines, except Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and French Wines, are to be accounted of the growth of the Levant, and to pay Cuſtoms accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In levying</hi> the Subſidy of Poundage, the Collector is to collect, receive and levy Five in the Hundred as a Generall Subſidy upon all Goods Inwards and Outwards, aſwell from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34528:11"/>the Engliſh and Scots Merchant, as from the Merchant-Stranger, and the Petty Cuſtoms of Three pence in the Pound more from all Strangers, ſo as the Merchant-Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for every Twelve pence to be paid by the Engliſh or Scots Merchants, upon every Pound or Twenty ſhillings ſterling, is to pay One ſhilling three pence, Subſidy and Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall pay for Native Commodities and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Coal,</hi> Pladding, Salmon, and all manner of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive-Commodities or Manufactures made thereof, to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or ſhipped Outwards, he is to collect from the Merchant-Stranger, Five in the Hundred, over and above the Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> and Petry-Cuſtoms aforeſaid; ſo as the Merchant-Stranger, for every Twelve pence to be paid by the Engliſh or Scots-Merchant, is to pay Two ſhillings three pence Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy and Cuſtoms: And the Merchant-Stranger for thoſe Commodities for which he is to pay double Subſidy, as Lead, Tin,<note place="margin">Double Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble petty Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</note> Woollen-Cloath, and all, or any Manufactures made of Wooll, or part Wooll, is alſo to pay double Petty-Cuſtoms, and upon Woollen-Cloath he is to pay more, an old Cuſtom of Fourteen pence upon every Cloath Exported, and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably upon new Draperies, as they are reckoned for a Cloath in the Inſtructions annexed to the Book of Rates.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Natives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas.</note>
               <hi>All Engliſh</hi> or Scots inhabiting beyond the Seas, and ſworn Subjects to forreign Princes, are to pay Cuſtoms and other Duties as Strangers, ſo long as they continue ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Denizens to pay ſtrangers Cuſtoms.</note>
               <hi>All Strangers</hi> made Denizens, are to pay all Cuſtoms and Subſidies as ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All great</hi> and ſmall Coal exported, being by Order of his Highneſs Councill in <hi>Scotland</hi> for the Government thereof, bearing date the Firſt of <hi>November,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coal to be computed by the Tun, not Chaldron.</note> 1655. rated to pay a certain Rate upon each Chaldron, containing Twenty hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred weight; Eſpeciall care therefore is to be had in levying thereof, That the Collector do not receive or take the ſame according to the Scots Chaldron, which is more or leſs in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places where ſuch Coal are ſhipped and laden, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the number of Tuns, or twenty hundred weights con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in every ſuch Chaldron.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34528:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coals ſhipt in ſtrangers Bottoms.</note>
               <hi>All Merchants</hi> Engliſh or Scots ſhipping out Coals for beyond the Seas in ſtrangers Bottoms, are to pay ſtrangers Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms. In the ſhipping therefore of the ſame, as alſo in all other caſes of the like nature it is to be noted,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch.</note>
               <hi>That all Ships wherein the moyetie or major part of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſtrangers, are to be accompted ſtrangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all Ships belonging to ſtrangers are to be accompted ſtrangers Bottoms, though</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scots <hi>built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all Ships belonging to</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scots <hi>Merchants, are to be accompted</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scots <hi>Bottoms, though For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all Ships of which any ſtranger is part Owner, are to be reckned ſtrangers Bottoms, though all the reſt of the Owners be</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scots.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What to be paid for Lead</note>
               <hi>All Lead</hi> exported whether by <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Scots,</hi> or by any Merchant ſtranger, is to pay over and above the Subſidy and Cuſtoms, an old Cuſtom of three pence in the Sow, which is two ſhillings upon the Fodder or twenty hundred weight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Beer</hi> ſhipped out by any <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Scots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beer.</note> beſides the two ſhillings Subſidy mentioned in the Book of Rates, is to pay eight ſhillings ſix pence more <hi>per</hi> Tun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Scots,</hi> and ten ſhillings by every ſtranger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tobaccoes of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations.</note>
               <hi>One penny per</hi> pound is to be levied on all Tobaccoes of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations beyond the Sea, and upon all other Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes of what Plantation ſoever, ſix pence in the pound. And to the end every Collector may have true Cognizance what is of Engliſh, and what of Forraign Plantations,<note place="margin">How to be tryed from Forraign.</note> he is to take notice that he is to paſſe no Tobaccoes to be of the Engliſh Plantations, but only ſuch as by ſufficient perſons ſhall be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted upon Oath ſo to be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There being</hi> a great difference in the Cuſtoms of <hi>Tauton</hi> Cottons and Bayes,<note place="margin">Bayes,</note> and the latter of them being very often ſhipped in the name of the former, the Collector is to have an eſpeciall care that for ſuch as are Bayes (in whatſoever name the Merchant may enter them) Cuſtom may be demanded and levied as for Bayes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Horſes, or live Cattell.</note>
               <hi>All Horſes</hi> and live Cattell imported, are to pay Subſidy,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34528:12"/>notwithſtanding the exception of freſh Fiſh and Beſtiall in the Act for Tunnage and Poundage; For that by freſh Fiſh, is meant only Fiſh unſalted, and by Beſtiall, freſh Fleſh for mans meat, killed or brought in unſalted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon all</hi> Ships brought in as Prize, whether taken by the States Ships,<note place="margin">Prize Goods and Ships.</note> or other Private Men of War, after condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, full Cuſtom is not only to be received for all Goods therein, as if they were imported by way of Merchandize, but alſo for the Ship, Tackle, Ordnance, and other furniture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſame, after the Rate of five <hi>per Cent.</hi> as the ſame ſhall be indifferently apprized.<note place="margin">Ships bought beyond the ſeas.</note> As alſo the like Cuſtom is to be received for all other Ships that are bought beyond the Seas, as the proper Goods of any perſon or Merchant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Prize Goods.</note>
               <hi>For all</hi> Goods brought in as Prize, no defalcation or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance from the quantity thereof, or out of the ſum of money due for Cuſtom and Subſidy by way of abatement, for being bad, damaged, or defective, is to be made or granted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All allowance</hi> to be made and given to Merchants for Wrappers upon ſhipping out old or new Draperies,<note place="margin">Wrappers.</note> are not to exceed the Directious and Inſtructions annexed to the Book of Rates: and upon all Goods exported, no allowance of five <hi>per Cent.</hi> is at any time to be given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The allowance</hi> of twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> is to be made for Leakage of Wines,<note place="margin">Twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> for Leakage.</note> (excepting Wines brought in as Prize, to which neither this, nor any other allowance is to be made) to Merchants, demanding the ſame by way of defalcation where no Wines are filled up on Ship-board, and care therefore is to be taken for preventing thereof. But in caſe any Merchant or other ſhall happen firſt to fill up his, or their Wines, then no allowance at all is to be made or given: And when and where it is, as aforeſaid, of right to be made and granted, the ſaid twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> is not to be taken or deducted out of the quantities of Wines, but out of the Moneys to be paid and received for the Subſidy thereof.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34528:12"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ships unlade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part, to pay for their whole lading.</note>
               <hi>If any</hi> Ship importing Forraign Goods or Merchandize into any Port of this Nation, ſhall happen to unlade or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge part of her Loading there, and intend afterward to tranſport the reſt over Sea; Entry is to be made of the whole, and Cuſtom paid accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods to be cleared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Engliſh Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, of wright and meaſure.</note>
               <hi>All Merchants,</hi> and other Perſons, clearing Goods at the Cuſtom-houſe, are to clear and pay their Cuſtom both for weight and meaſure according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Standard, which is that, mentioned and expreſſed in the Book of Rates; that is to ſay, All Goods which pay by meaſure are to be cleared no otherwiſe then according to the Buſhell, which contains eight Gallons <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or eight Quarts <hi>Scots;</hi> And to all other Goods paying Cuſtom by the hundreth weight, that there be allowed and accompted to the hundred ſubtle, but five ſcore, and to the hundred weight groſs, five ſcore and twelve pounds, and for other Goods by the Tun weight, but twenty hundred weight of one hundred and twelve pounds to each hundred; to the Tun of meaſure, but two hundred fifty two Gallons; and to the meaſure of Ells and Yards, but according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Standard of an Ell and a Yard.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The contents of a Tun.</note>Only it is to be noted, That two Buts and Pipes, albeit two of them do not exactly contain one Tun, are nevertheleſſe to pay Cuſtom for one Tun, in like manner as four Hogſheds, three Puncheons, ſix Teirces, and eight quarter Casks, of what ſort ſoever, are to paſſe and pay for a Tun, although the Gage be not ſo much.</p>
            <p>But all Goods coming in uncertain and unuſuall Cask which are to pay by the Tun, Hogſhead, Pipe, or Barrell,<note place="margin">Uncertain Casks to be gaged.</note> are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced unto the aforeſaid number of Gallons, to make a Tun And where the Book of Rates directs any Commodity to pay by the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> or other Outlandiſh meaſure, there only is the Cuſtom to be collected accordingly; but upon all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities according to the reſpective weights and meaſures aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where any</hi> Goods and Merchandize ſhall be imported or exported,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Goods</hi> ad va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem.</note> and the ſame not rated or valued in the Book of Rates, there and in ſuch caſe, the Collector is to ſet the value
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34528:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon the Goods, in which he is to have regard unto the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that ſhall accrue unto the Commonwealth, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to ſet the Rate and value; but in no caſe to ſet the Rate and value of any Goods below the intrinſecall value or worth thereof, nor any Manufacture imported, at leaſt then double the intrinſecall value thereof, whether the ſame be imported by <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scots</hi> Linnen how to be rated.</note> 
               <hi>Scots,</hi> or Stangers. But in the caſe of <hi>Scots</hi> Linnen ſhipped out, the Collector of the Port where any ſuch Linnen ſhall be exported, is to ſet down the true value thereof; And if the Merchant be not content with ſuch valuing thereof, the Merchant is to take his Oath of the value thereof, and according to the value depoſed by the Merchant, the Collector is to receive the Cuſtoms at five pound for each hundred pounds worth, according to an Order of his Highneſſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill in <hi>Scotland</hi> for the Government thereof, bearing date the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And becauſe</hi> ſundry Commodities of this nature have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been rated, and do now pay in <hi>England,</hi> as is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after expreſſed, The Collector is therefore to take care,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What to be payed for ſnowt Tow.</note>
               <hi>That Snowt</hi> Tow be rated at fourty ſhillings <hi>per Cent.</hi> and pay Cuſtom accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all</hi> Pan-tiles brought from <hi>Holland,</hi> or elſwhere, be rated,<note place="margin">Pan-tiles.</note> and pay after the Rate of eighty pounds <hi>per</hi> Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all Logwood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Log-wood.</note>
               <hi>alias</hi> Blockwood, or Campeachy Wood be rated, and pay after the rate of Eighty pounds <hi>per</hi> Tun.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Lead-oare</hi> be rated at the value of Six pounds thirteen ſhillings four pence <hi>per</hi> Tun,<note place="margin">Lead-Oare.</note> containing Twenty hundred weight, and paid after that rate by <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots.</hi> And the ſame being a Native Commodity, Strangers therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Exportation are to pay double Subſidy, and double petty-Cuſtoms: That is to ſay, Every Merchant ſtranger is to pay the duty for every Tun of the ſaid Lead-oare, after the rate or value of Thirteen pounds ſix ſhillings and eight pence, beſides double petty-Cuſtoms, which is Six pence upon every Twenty ſhillings value, according to that rate.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34528:13"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coleſeed, and Coleſeed Oyls.</note>
               <hi>That all Coleſeed Oyls</hi> Imported, and Coleſeed Exported, be rated, and pay as Rapeſeed Oyls, and Rapeſeed Outwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Horſes</hi> are to be permitted Exportation upon Licence from his Highneſſe or Council,<note place="margin">Horſes.</note> to any the Engliſh Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> upon payment of Twenty ſhillings Cuſtom for each Horſe, according to an Ordinance of his Highneſſe and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, dated the 30. of <hi>January,</hi> 1653.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Repayment of half-ſubſidy.</note>
               <hi>No Repayment</hi> of any half Subſidy upon the Exporting of Goods formerly Imported, is to be made unto any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant whatſoever, without the expreſſe Order and Direction of the Commiſſioners therein. Yet, foraſmuch as ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty may attend the doing thereof, by reaſon of the diſtance of the Port where ſuch Goods may happen to be Exported or ſhipped our, unleſſe ſomewhat be prepared and done upon the Place in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>The Collector therefore of the Port where ſuch Goods ſhall happen to be Exported, and half Subſidy demanded, is to ſatisfie himſelf whether the Goods upon which the ſaid half-Subſidy is to be repaid (if exported by, or for a Strangers Accompt) were Imported within Nine moneths; and (if by, and for an Engliſh or Scotſ-man's Accompt) within Twelve moneths of no? The computation of which Nine or Twelve months is to be made from the day of the Entry of the Goods Inwards, whether by ſight or perfect Warrant, to the day of the ſhipping them on board Outward, and not the date of the Certificate: And then he is together with the Cheque of the ſame Port, to make a Certificate under their Hands, that ſuch Goods were entred and paid Cuſtom, and all other Duties up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Importation thereof; In which Certificate is to be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned and expreſſed the time when the ſame were Imported, by whom, the Quantity and Quality of the ſaid Goods, in words at length, and not in figures.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſaid Certificate, the Merchant, or ſome for him that can depoſe the ſame, is to make Oath that the Goods which he intendeth to Export, are the ſame mentioned in the Certificate, and for which the full Subſidy, and other Duties due upon the Importation, were paid; as alſo whether the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34528:14"/>ſaid Goods have been contracted for, or ſold, and to whom, and for whoſe account the ſame are to be ſhipped and export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But if upon ſuch examination and enquiry (as he ſhall think fit to make upon Oath in this matter) it ſhall appear unto him, that ſuch Goods have been fold unto, or in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of any Shop-keeper, or Retailor of the ſame Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, or that the Property, Form or Nature of ſuch Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity hath in any wiſe been altered, mingled, amended, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, then he is to forbear proceeding any further; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that in all and every ſuch caſe, there is no half-Subſidy to be repaid, but the Merchant is to pay his Cuſtom Outwards, unleſs in caſe of Goods to be Exported by the Importer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by free Cocquet, according to the ſeventh Article annexed to the Book of Rates. But where the repayment of the half-Subſidy ſhall truly and really appear to be due and of right belonging, according to the ſeveral circumſtances, before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, Then and there the Collector ſhall go on to make out unto the Merchant a Cetrificate, Cocquet, and Debenter in manner and form following.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <p>In the <hi>Roſemary-tree</hi> of <hi>Leith, Anthony Ball</hi> Mr. for <hi>Maligo. David Cuningham,</hi> Ind.</p>
                  <p>Five Bails, containing twenty hundred Els Net Linnen.</p>
                  <p>The Subſidy Inward for twenty hundred Ells Net Linnen was paid by <hi>David Cuningham</hi> the eight and twentieth day of <hi>September</hi> laſt paſt.<note place="margin">Certificate.</note>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Written <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> of <hi>December, 1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Juravit <hi>David Cuningham,</hi> or <hi>E. F.</hi> his Servant. The Goods above mentioned in this Certificate to be ſhipped out, are the ſame which paid Cuſtoms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and are to be tranſported and ſent beyond the Seas, for the proper accompt of the ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Cuningham,</hi> without any pre-contract for the ſame.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34528:14"/>
                  <head>Form of the Cocquet.</head>
                  <p>KNow ye, That <hi>David Cuningham</hi> Ind. for five Bails <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">Cocques.</note> twenty hundred Ells of Linnen Cloath Net, late in this Port unladen, and now to be ſhipped in the <hi>Roſemary-tree</hi> of <hi>Leith, Anthony Ball</hi> Maſter for <hi>Maligo,</hi> paid all Duties at the firſt Diſcharge, the eight and twentieth day of <hi>September</hi> laſt paſt. Dated the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 1655.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>Form of the Debentur.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>LEITH.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAvid Cuningham</hi> did Enter with us the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1655.</hi> in the <hi>Roſemary-tree</hi> of <hi>Leith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Debentur.</note> 
                     <hi>Anthony Ball</hi> Maſter, for <hi>Maligo,</hi> five Bails, containing twenty hundred Ells of Linnen Cloath Net, the Subſiay whereof was paid Inwards by the ſaid <hi>David Cuningham</hi> Ind. the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1655.</hi> laſt paſt, as doth appear by the Certificate thereof; And for farther manifeſtation of his juſt dealing herein he hath alſo taken Oath before <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Cuſtom-houſe Leith</hi>
                        <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which Debenter afterward the Searcher or Waiter that ſhipped off the ſaid Goods, is to indorſe or certifie the time when, and the name of the Ship in which they were ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; And after the ſaid Ships departure from the Coaſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or arrival of the Goods in ſome Port beyond the Seas, the Merchant himſelf, and no other perſon, is to bring in the Certificate of the Searcher or Waiter, and Debenter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, unto the Commiſſioners, and making Oath before them, That the Goods expreſſed in the Debenter and Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34528:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>aforeſaid, thereunto annexed, are really ſhipped out, both for quality &amp; quantity, and are not, nor any part thereof (ſince they were laſt ſhipped out) re-landed in any Port or Creek in <hi>England, Wales,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> Then the Commiſſioners will give Warrant unto the reſpective Collectors (from, or out of whoſe Port the ſame was ſhipped) for re-payment back of the half-Subſidy. According to which Order, ſuch Collector within one moneth after, in caſe nothing ſhall or may in that time appear which may juſtly impede or hinder the doing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is to make re payment of the ſame accordingly, taking the Receipts of the Merchant, or of his known Factor or Agent, on the backſide of the Debenter for ſo much as ſhall be paid unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the ſeventh Article</hi> of Inſtructions annexed to the Book of Rates,<note place="margin">Goods impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported free of Cuſtoms.</note> it is directed, That if a Merchant having duly paid all Duties Inwards, And, in regard of bad Sales, ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to keep the ſaid Goods, or any part thereof in his hands, without alteration of property, after the ſpace of a year be clapſed; in that caſe he is to be permitted to ſhip the ſame out for ſome parts beyond the Seas (if he ſo think fit) without payment of any Subſidy for the ſame Outwards, upon due proof that the ſame was duly Entred, and Subſidy paid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: But before the Merchant have any free Cocquet to that purpoſe, a Certificate is to be made out, and ſubſcribed by the Collector, of the time when ſuch Goods were import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as alſo that the Cuſtoms thereof were by him received; And in the ſaid Certificate is to be expreſſed, the Quantity and Quality of Goods Imported, and deſired to be Exported, as alſo upon the ſame the Oath of the party that paid the Cuſtom, affirming it to be paid and the Oath of the Proprietors, and no other perſon is to be taken that the ſaid Goods are not ſold and contracted for, nor altered in the Quality ſince they were firſt imported, and that they ſhall (and are to) be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porred upon his own proper accompt; All which reſpectively being duly obſerved and performed in the preſence of the Cheque, the Collector and Cheque are then to give and grant a free Cocquet for paſſing out ſuch Goods as ſhall be deſired;<note place="margin">The Free Cocquet.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34528:15"/>but notice is to be taken that no ſuch free Cocquet is to be granted to any Merchant ſtranger after his Goods have been Imported above nine moneths, that being the time limited in the ſecond Article annexed to the Book of Rates, to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſtranger for Exportation of his Goods. The Form of the Certificate and Oath is to be in manner and form fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: <hi>(VIZ.)</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>In the <hi>Samuel</hi> of <hi>Preſton-Pans, G. Wilſon</hi> Mr. for <hi>Campveer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Form of the Certificate and Oath.</note> 
                     <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Andro Henderſon,</hi> Ind.</p>
                  <p>Two Bails containing ten hundred Ells of Vittery-Canvas. The Subſidy Inwards for ten hundred Ells of Vittery Canvas was paid by <hi>Andro Henderſon</hi> Ind. the ſixth of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1654.</hi> Written the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1655.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Juravit, <hi>Andro Henderſon,</hi> The Goods above-mentioned have paid full Cuſtom Inwards, and are to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported on his own accompt, without alteration of property, or contract for the ſame.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>KNow ye, That <hi>Andrew Henderſon</hi> for two Bails,<note place="margin">The Form of the free Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining two hundred Ells of Vittery Canvas Net, paid all Duties Inward the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1654.</hi> and now to be ſhipped in the <hi>Samuel</hi> of <hi>Preſton Pans, George Wilſon</hi> Maſter, for <hi>Campveer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <hi>1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What meant by Alteration of Quality and Property</note>By <hi>Alteration of Quality</hi> is to be underſtood, the altering the condition of it from that it was in when it was Imported, whether by making it into any Manufacture, Commodity, other form or quality whatſoever: As I lax and Hemp Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported ſo, and afterwards made, the firſt of them into Cloath,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34528:16"/>and the latter into Yarn, Ropes or Twine. And ſo likewiſe Linnen Cloath Imported, afterwards cut and made into Shirts, Sheets, or other neceſſaries. And in like manner all Goods dyed, dreſſed, or further manufactured after their firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, are all altered in their Quality. And Goods are then altered in their Property, when the ſame have been either ſold or contracted for.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note>In paſſing of Goods, the Collectors and other Officers are to underſtand by Goods prohibited to be Exported, Monies, Bullion, Plate, Jewels, Woollen-Yarn, and Cloath undreſſed, Horſes, Mares, Geldings, Oxen, Kine, Sheep, Copper, Braſſe, Bell-mettal, Pan-mettal, Gun-mettal, Shruffe, white Aſhes, Butter, Cheeſe, Wood, Corn (when it is above the Price limitted by Statute.) As alſo Leather, Hides, Tallow and all things made thereof, Skins of Sheep, Pelts, and Skins of Stags, Hindes, Bucks, Does or Fawn, Goats or Kid, Wool, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted-Yarn, Woollen-Flocks, Wool-Fells; Fullers-Earth and Clay of what kind ſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What meant by Grocery &amp; ſaltery Wares</note>It is further to be noted, That by Grocery and Saltery Wares are meant, Forreign Commodities only, which have been formerly brought from beyond the Seas, and the Duties paid inwards, and that no Merchandize or Manufacture of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> are to paſſe under thoſe general names.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:34528:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS,</hi> For the <hi>COLLECTORS</hi> or Sub-Commiſsioners for <hi>EXCIZE</hi> of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Goods upon Importation, or Sale, reſpectively.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sub-Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners how to proceed in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He buſineſſe</hi> of Exciſe this Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put under the management of one and the ſame Perſons; The Collectors in the ſeverall Ports are the ſame with the Sub-Commiſſioners, and in like manner impowered for execution of their Truſts accordingly: In the levying and collection of the duty of Excize, the ſeverall Collectors, or Sub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners appointed for doing thereof, in the reſpective Ports of this Nation, are to Demand, Receive, Gather, Levy, and Collect the ſame, according to the ſeverall Rates mentioned and expreſſed in, and by an Order and Declaration of His Highneſſe the Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> and his Councill; Dated the Two and twentieth day of <hi>May,</hi> 1655. <hi>Entituled, An Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe, and his Councill, for the Collecting of the Exciſe in</hi> Scotland. And further to obſerve, according to the power given them from the Commiſſioners, either by their reſpective Commiſſions, or theſe preſent Inſtructions, and no further; all ſuch Rules as are directed and appointed in and by the Order and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Highneſſe and Councill aforeſaid, or any other Act, Ordinance, Order, or Declaration, aſwell of his Highneſſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34528:17"/>as of Parliament, which were in force the ſecond day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> 1654. in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtom houſe how to be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
               <hi>The Cuſtom-houſe</hi> in every Port is ſo to be fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, as that the ſame may ſerve and be imployed alſo for managing the buſineſſe of Excize; and for this cauſe and reaſon, ſhall upon all week dayes be kept open from eight of the Clock in the Morning, till twelve at Noon, and from two of the Clock in the Afternoon,<note place="margin">How long kept open.</note> till ſix at Night, for the Entring and Regiſtring the Goods, Wares, and Merchandizes, with the Names, and Sirnames, aſwell of the Importers, as of the Sellers, and Buyers of the ſeverall Goods, Wares, and Commodities Excizable, their quantities, and values, as for the receiving of all Moneys which ſhall be due and payable thereupon, and for doing other things neceſſary to be done, for, and concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the</hi> Arrivall and after the Entry of any Ship with Goods Inwards,<note place="margin">Merchants Importers, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Goods, to give three Bills as to Excize.</note> from any Parts beyond the Seas, every Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Importer, (if he be purely a Merchant, and ſo not to pay any Excize untill Sale) is in like manner, as for the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, to deliver in to the Collector and Cheque three Bills of Entry, under his own hand, (or the hand of ſuch other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Perſons, as by Deed or Writing under his hand and Seal ſhall be deputed thereunto) mentioning the name of the Ship, and of the Maſter, whence, and from what place it was Fraighted, with the Marks, Numbers, Fardels, Bulk, or Pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Margent, and the true quantity and quality of the Goods therein contained, in words at length, and not in Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures; two of which Bills, (as in the buſineſſe of Cuſtoms) ſhall be Signed by the Collector, and Cheque reſpectively, and delivered afterwards to each other to be numbred, filed, and kept as an originall Voucher for the Excize; And the third being Signed by them both, ſhall be the Waiters warrant for the delivery of the ſame to the Merchant: This is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Merchant Importer only;<note place="margin">Merchants paying Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize upon En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, how many.</note> for where Goods pay Excize aſwell as Cuſtoms upon Entry, one and the ſame Bills (being three only in number) given for Cuſtoms, will ſerve alſo for Excize.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34528:17"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Entries of Merchant Importers in what manner to be placed in the Sub-Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors Book.</note>
               <hi>If the Merchant</hi> Importer be purely a Merchant, then upon his Entry made, as aforeſaid, he is to be permitted to take up and receive his Goods forthwith, without payment of any Excize: And the Collector ſhall not need for all Entries of this kind, to make any Entries in his Caſh, or day Book diſtinct from that of the Cuſtoms, but only to draw a blank Line with pricks, or otherwiſe, from the ſaid Cuſtom Entry through the Column of the ſaid Book, which is appointed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the Receipts of Excize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Merchant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer how to Enter and pay.</note>
               <hi>But if</hi> the Merchant Importer ſhall happen to be either a Shop-keeper, or Retailer of the Commodities he Imports, the Collector and Cheque having upon delivery in of his Bills of Entry caſt up the ſum, or ſums unto which the Excize of the Goods mentioned in the ſaid Bills ſhall amount unto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered their Bills ſo caſt, unto each other reſpectively,<note place="margin">In what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ſame ſhal be placed to accompt.</note> (as was directed before, as to Cuſtoms) the Collector ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive the Excize due thereupon, and make Entry of the ſame in his Caſh or day Book, not making a diſtinct Entry from the Cuſtoms, but having expreſſed the rate or value of the Excize, different from the Cuſtom, next and immediately below the Entry of the ſame, as to Cuſtoms, ſhall draw out and place the totall due, or received for Excize in an equall Line with that of the Cuſtoms, but in the Column of the Book aforeſaid, appointed and deſigned for the Receipts of Excize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Merchant ſtranger, or Planter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring.</note>
               <hi>But if</hi> it ſo fall out that the Merchant or Importer be ſome Perſon living beyong the Seas, a Planter in the Weſt-<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> or <hi>Virgina,</hi> an unknown Perſon, either having no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain habitation (that is to ſay) not known to be an able or ſufficient Merchant, or elſe having no conſtant Family in the Town or Port where he ſhall Enter his Goods; ſuch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant is either to pay down the Excize of his Goods, or elſe to give Bond to the Collector, with ſufficient Security,<note place="margin">To pay Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, or give Bond.</note> or Caution for the payment of the Excize, before he be admitted to take up his Goods, or receive any warrant for doing thereof.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:34528:18"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Such Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant being unable, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to give Bond, or pay, his Goods are to be taken up and landed.</note>
               <hi>If any Planter,</hi> or unknown perſon, as aforeſaid, ſhall not be able, or ſhall refuſe to give Bond, or to pay Excize upon Entry, as aforeſaid, then and in ſuch caſe, the Collector is to cauſe the Goods to be taken up and landed; And after due notice taken of the Quantity and Quality of the Goods, in the preſence of the Owner, or ſome other appointed by him; or upon refuſall of himſelf, or any other for him to be preſent, in the preſence of other two good witneſſes, to houſe and diſpoſe of the ſame in ſome ſitting Ware-houſe, untill either Bond be given, or Excize fully paid for the ſame, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shop-keeper to carry his Goods to his own houſe.</note>
               <hi>Eſpeciall care</hi> is to be had and taken, that the Shop-keeper upon Entry, and clearing of his Goods Inwards, at the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them, do carry his Goods to his own Shop directly, and is not to be permitted to houſe and lay up the ſame in any other Houſe, Shop, Store-houſe, or other place whatſoever, without acquainting the Collector and Cheque therewith. In like manner, no Merchant who is purely ſuch, no Planter or unknown Merchant,<note place="margin">No Merchant to lodge his Goods with a Retailer.</note> is to be permitted to houſe or diſpoſe of his Goods, Wares or Merchandizes, in the Houſe, Shop, Ware-houſe, or any other place, of, or belonging to any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer of the ſame Commodity, without firſt making the Collector and Cheque in like manner acquainted therewith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods ſold, how to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</note>
               <hi>When any Goods</hi> aforeſaid, come to the conſumption or ſale, the Merchant (who is purely a Merchant, and who was perimitted to land and take up his Goods without payment of any Excize) ſhall (before he be permitted to deliver all or any of the ſame) bring and deliver to the Collector and Cheque, two Bills of Entry, ſigned under his own hand (or the hand of his Servant, or other perſon whom he ſhall firſt authorize under his hand, to be filed in the Office of Excize to that purpoſe, and for whoſe Act he ſhall be anſwerable) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the Quantity, Weight and Meaſure of his Goods ſold, and to whom, their ſeveral ſpecies, ſortments and kinds, and the price at which they are ſold in caſe they be goods, which pay Excize <hi>ad valorem;</hi> Upon each of which Bills, the Collector and Cheque having caſt up and written the Sum or Sums due and payable for Excize of the ſaid Goods, and given each other
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34528:18"/>the reſpective Bills caſt up by either of them (as is directed in caſe of Entries, as to Cuſtoms, as aforeſaid) the Collector forthwith receiving the ſaid Sum or Sums due thereupon, ſhall afterwards make Entry of the ſame in his Caſh or Day-Book, by putting or placing the Sum aforeſaid,<note place="margin">The Moneys received how placed to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. What warrant thereupon ſhal be made.</note> in the Column for Receipts of Excize, and drawing a blank line with pricks, or other wayes, through that of the Cuſtoms; And then the Collector and Cheque ſhall joyntly make and ſign a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Ticket or Warrant for delivery thereof; Which Warrant is to contain the Quantity and Quality of the Goods ſold, with the name of the Buyer, and of his place of Reſidence or Habitation, and to be onely in force for that particular Parcell, and for that day only: The ſame to be in manner and form fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>LEITH.
<date>
                           <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Entry upon ſale.</note>
                     <hi>SOld unto</hi> C. D. <hi>of</hi> Edinburgh</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of the Ticket or Warrant.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Excize-Office in <hi>Leith.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu may deliver unto <hi>C. B.</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> for which the duty of Excize is paid this day, according to the Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, with the advice and conſent of his Councill, bearing date the two and twentieth day of <hi>May, 1655.</hi> This Ticket to ſerve onely for this day, and this Parcell, or elſe to be void.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>To <hi>A. B.</hi> Merchant. <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:34528:19"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods ſold to ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, how to be entred.</note>
               <hi>If the quantity</hi> of Goods ſold, and certified to be ſo (as aforeſaid) is to be delivered unto more than one perſon Buyer thereof, the Collector and Cheque are (although the ſame be but one and the ſame Parcell) to make and give as many ſeverall Tickets, as there are perſons unto whom the Goods are ſold. And the Merchant therefore is to make either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Entryes of his Sales, or elſe one generall one, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Goods ſold, with the ſeverall Quantities or Parcels thereof, which are to be delivered unto the reſpective Buyers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sufferance in what caſe to be granted.</note>
               <hi>If any Merchant</hi> or Importer, ſhall ſell any Goods, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he cannot aſcertain the perfect weight and meaſure of the ſame, then a Bill of Sufferance ſhall be granted, and an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer is to be ſent to deliver and take accompt of the perfect weight and meaſure, and certifie the ſame unto the Collector and Cheque;<note place="margin">Merchant to make his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Entry within <hi>28.</hi> dayes, and the buyer pay his Excize, Or elſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt</note> And the Merchant ſhall within 28. dayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, make a perfect Entry, and the Buyer pay the full Excize, or elſe both of them to be proceeded againſt, as by the 21. Article of the Act of Parliament for Excize, of the 14. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649. is directed and appointed; Which 21. Article, the Collector or Sub-Commiſſioner is fully in every part thereof, to put, or cauſe to be put in Execution, when, and as often as the ſame ſhall by them be thought fit and requiſit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To whom ſufferance ſhall be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>But care is to be had, that no ſufferance be granted unto any perſons, but ſuch as ſhall either depoſire ſo much as the Excize may probably amount unto, or elſe ſhall (or are known to be) perſons reſponſible, and of ability to make good the Duty which ſhall, or may be due for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods having before paid Excize, how to be entred and paſſed.</note>
               <hi>If ſale</hi> happen to be made of any Goods, which before had paid Excize either upon the Importing, or elſe in <hi>England,</hi> or ſome other Port of this Nation, or which ſhall be part of a greater Quantity or Parcell formerly cleared, Entry, Ticker or Warrant is to be made, as aforeſaid, in every particular, for Goods lyable to payment of Excize; Except that beſides, there is no Money to be received, and that the Entry in that caſe is not to be entred in the Caſh or Day-Book; but in a Waſte-Book (which is therefore to be kept purpoſely for Tickets
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34528:19"/>granted for delivery of Goods, which before had paid Excize) the Seller or Deliverer is to make Oath before the Collector and Cheque, that the Goods hy him ſold and intended to be delivered, are all of them ſuch as had <hi>bond fide</hi> paid Excize, and then the Warrant or Ticket for Delivery of the ſame (in which alwayes mention is to be made, when, or in what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, or at what place the ſame paid Duty) is to be iſſued in manner and form following, <hi>(V I Z.)</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>Form of a Ticket for Goods cleared before.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Excize-Office,</hi> Leith.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You may deliver this day unto</hi> E.F. <hi>to be ſent for <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> being then cleared, or being part of a greater Parcell, cleared upon Accompt (ſuch or juch a day) or being entred Inwards, the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> or cleared at</hi> London, <hi>as</hi> per <hi>Certificate dated <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> for which time and Parcell, this Ticket is onely to ſerve; or elſe to be ſold, the duty of Excize being paid, according to the Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, with the advice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, bearing date the</hi> 22. <hi>day of</hi> May, 1655. <hi>Dated this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> One thouſand, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>To A. B. Merchant. A. B. <hi>Collector.</hi> C. D. <hi>Cheque.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Goods to be romaged without Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</note>As no Goods after they are ſold, are to be permitted, to be delivered unto any the buyers thereof, without Ticket or Warrant (which is to be valid no longer time than that day on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in which the ſaid Ticket is taken out, as to the delivery of the Goods) So all Goods unſold, or which the Duty of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize hath before at any time been paid, are not to be roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, removed or ſent from one Houſe, Town, Part or Place to another, without a Ticket or Warrant for doing thereof; and if ſo, to be ſeized and ſecured. But yet for accommodation of Trade, it is thought fit, that the ſtrictneſs of the Law in this particular be relaxed.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34528:20"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Except Goods bought of ſhop-keepers, or where no fraud is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended;</note>Where any Shop-keepers, living in one and the ſame place, Town or Burgh, ſhall buy Goods of one another; Or, where any Goods are bought in ſmall Parcels from any Shop keeper by any other, and where otherways upon Examination, no fraud ſhall appear intended to have been practiſed in prejudice of the Commonwealth; And to this purpoſe therefore, and for the better evincing of the truth in this particular, or in caſe of Goods hindred by wind, weather, or otherways beyond the time mentioned in any Ticket that ſhall be given,<note place="margin">Which the collector is impowered to examine.</note> the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſhall cauſe ſuch perſons to be ſummoned before him, as he ſhall think or ſuppoſe to be any ways able to give teſtimony in the caſe; And them to examine upon oath for the diſcovery of the whole and true matter of fact which ſhall then fall under Queſtion before him, as to Equity and Juſtice ſhall appertain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Any Merchant</hi> or Importer, making Entry of any Goods, in any Port Town,<note place="margin">Goods ſent by land-carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note> and afterwards carrying the ſame by Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage to any other Port or Place, Town or Burgh of this Nation, ſhall have a particular Warrant or Ticket for doing thereof, when, and according as his Goods ſhall be carryed, whether in greater or leſſer Parcels; Which Ticket or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is to continue for no longer time than the Goods may reaſonably be on the way from one place to another, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to be expreſt in the body thereof, at the diſcretion of the Collectors, as aforeſaid, in manner following;</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of a Ticket by Land carriage.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Excize-Office,</hi> Leith.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>E. F. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>is permitted to ſend by land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage, by <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Carrier for <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> being Entred, or being part of a Parcell here Extred by <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> And for which the Duty of Excize was paid at the value of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> This Ticket to be in force <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> dayes, and no longer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>
                           <hi>this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc> _____ </desc>
                              </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc> _____ </desc>
                              </gap> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix huudred and fifty</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>A.B. <hi>Collector.</hi> C.D. <hi>Cheque.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:34528:20"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No more than one Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket given for one parcel.</note>The like form to be uſed, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> for Goods ſent by Land-carriage, which had paid Excize either then, (when ſent) or before upon ſale; But eſpecially care is to be had, that no more but one Ticket be granted for one parcell of Goods; and if the ſame ſhould happen to be loſt, no other,<note place="margin">That loſt, a new one to be given.</note> nor new one is to be given, before Oath be firſt made thereof before the Collector and Cheque, That the ſame is <hi>re verâ</hi> loſt indeed, or elſe, that no uſe at all had been made thereof; and then, and not before, the Collector and Cheque ſhall give a new Ticket, in which ſtill ſignification ſhall be made that there had already (and the time expreſſed when there had) a Ticket before been given and granted for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> to be allowed as to Excize.</note>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> and Merchandizes which pay Subſidy of Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and upon which Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> is uſually allowed, by the Eighteenth Article annexed to the Book of Rates for Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, are to be poſted to Accompt of the Merchant Importer, or elſe to pay Excize reſpectively, according to their full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, without any ſuch allowance at all, ſo as the Accompt of the Merchant Importer (who is purely a Merchant) is to be charged with. And the Merchant Importer who is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer, or lyable to pay this duty, upon Importation is to pay Excize for Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> more than either of them paid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy Inwards, there being no Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> to be allowed as to Excize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No allowance for damage or defects upon Importation, unleſſe the Merchant clear his whole parcel.</note>
               <hi>No Merchant Importer</hi> (though he be purely ſuch) is to have any allowance made for damage of his Tobacco, or defects of his Wines upon the Importation, but ſale of them, unleſſe he ſhall clear and pay Excize down for the whole parcell of Tobacco or Wines he ſhall have on his hands, or ſhall then import.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Outs, or Twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize.</note>
               <hi>Whenſoever</hi> any Wines or Oyls ſhall be brought in upon Accompt of the Merchant (who is purely ſuch) the ſame are to be entred fully, according to the contents of the Casks, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſame be not full, and ſo to be poſted to his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt: But if the Merchant Importer be one who is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon landing of his Goods, to pay down the Excize of the ſame, then the Casks (which are not full, nor yet wholly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34528:21"/>empty) are to be gaged, and Excize to be paid for ſo much Wine or Oyls, as the ſame ſhall be found to contain, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither Outs, nor any Twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> to be allowed as to Excize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods paying Excize <hi>ad valorem.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>The Five per Cent.</hi> payable upon all Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes Imported, or to be Imported, ment oned in the Book of Rates for the Cuſtoms, but not ſpecified in the Rates of Excize, is to be levyed, raiſed and received, not according to the value any ſuch Commodities are rated at in the ſaid Book of Rates for the Cuſtoms, but according to the value as they, or any of them ſhall be ſold at a price by the Merchant, to the firſt Bayer thereof, where there is a Buyer; but where the ſame ſhall happen to pay preſently upon the Importation, then according to the higheſt price, the ſaid Goods in their ſeveral ſpecies, ſortment and kind, were laſt ſold at ſix moneths before, or that elſe the ſame beareth in the Mercat; the election whereof, as ſhall be moſt for the advantage of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is to be taken and received by the Collector or Sub-Commiſſioner.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Damaged To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baccoes, and</note>
               <hi>In making</hi> allowance for damaged Tobacco, or decayed Wines, notice is to be had, that there is nothing to be abated upon Tobaccoes but for over weight by ſand, ſtones, dirt or water.<note place="margin">Defective Wines.</note> And that all Wines being taſted, are to be returned, according to the ſeveral qualities and conditions following, and the Excize thereupon to be rated and paid as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WINES
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paſſable,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Defective,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Decayed,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fit only for the Sull,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> 
               <hi>To pay</hi>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>L.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>S.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>D.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> per <hi>Tun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from this Rule none of the Collectors, or Sub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners are to vary at any time, without ſpecial Order and Direction of the Commiſſioners themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34528:21"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Damaged To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baccoes, or Wines, to be delivered forthwith.</note>
               <hi>When any</hi> Tobaccoes or Wine, after ſale, and before delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof from the Merchant, ſhall be viewed or taſted, the Officer or Officers to be appointed by the Collector for doing thereof, ſhall take care and ſee the very ſame Numerical To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco and Wines delivered unto the Buyer, and no other; nor that any part or parcel of ſuch damaged Tobacco, or decayed Wines be left in the hands of the Merchant, and other deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in ſtead or lieu thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No allowance for goods once in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Buyer.</note>
               <hi>No allowance</hi> or defalcation of Excize is to be made upon any Goods, Wares or Merchandize for Leakage, Waſte, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, Defect or other accident whatſoever, after the ſame hath been once ſold and in the poſſeſſion and cuſtody of the Buyer therof: Neither is ſuch Buyer to be permitted to return any bad Wines remaining on his hands, (which had formerly paid Excize) unto the Merchant or Importer, and to receive from him or them new or freſh VVines in lieu of the ſame, without payment of the duty of thoſe new or freſh Wines, or ſo much (according to the condition and rate ſet as aforeſaid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the returned Wines) as the full Excize of the ſame Wine ſhal amount unto:<note place="margin">No exchange to be made of good for bad Wines, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out payment of the duty of ſound ones.</note> As ſuppoſe the Buyer make return of an Hogſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Wine fit only to diſtill, and receive a good one in ſtead thereof, in this caſe the rate of the bad Hogſhead being Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen ſhillings ſix pence, there will remain then to be paid more Twelve ſhillings ſix pence, which compleats the ſum of Thirty ſhillings, the full rate of a good Hogſhead of Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bills of Store and Portage to be charged to accompt, or elſe pay Excize.</note>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> paſſed by Bill of Store, Portage, or otherwiſe, as to the freeing them of Cuſtoms, are nevertheleſſe to be charged on accompt of the Merchant Importer, or elſe pay Excize reſpectively, as in all other caſes, as if the ſame had not been paſſed by any ſuch Bills, or otherwiſe at all, but then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34528:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS</hi> To the <hi>COLLECTORLS,</hi> or <hi>SUB-COMMISSIONERS</hi> of <hi>EXCIZE,</hi> as to Goods Outwards for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be entred.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Merchant Retailer,</hi> Shop-keeper, or other, may when, and as often as he ſhall deſire, ſhip out any Goods, Wares, or Commodities excizable, unto any Parts beyond the Seas, making Entry, and doing otherwiſe in all particulars as is required in the buſineſſe of the Cuſtoms for, and upon the ſhipping out of any Goods or Merchandize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No more then entred to be ſhipped on board.</note>But foraſmuch as the Merchants Accompts are to have ſo much credit as there ſhall be Goods at any time ſhipped out, or elſe that the Excize paid for theſe Goods is to be re-paid, eſpeciall care is to be taken, That neither more nor leſſe Goods be permitted at any time to be ſhipped, or carried on board any Ship or Veſſel, than ſhall be mentioned and expreſſed in the particular Entry Outwards of the Exporter, and ſo in the Warrant of the Collector and Cheque upon that Entry.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And Bond to be firſt given.</note>That before the ſhipping out of any Goods or Merchandizes which have not paid the duty of Excize, a ſufficient Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Law be entred into by the Merchant or Exporter ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out ſuch Goods, wherein he ſhall be bound either by himſelf, or elſe with ſufficient Caution (as ſhall be thought
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34528:22"/>fit and approved of by the Collector) in ſuch ſum of Money as ſhall amount to double the value of the ſaid Goods, with condition, That the ſame ſhall be diſcharged at ſome Port or Place beyond the Seas; And that he will by Oath or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe make due proof thereof before the Commiſſioners, or any they ſhall appoint, within ſuch convenient ſpace of time after, as ſhall be agreed upon by the Merchant and Collector for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, the ſame to be inſerted and mentioned in the ſaid Bond.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Repayment of Excize.</note>That no re-payment of Excize for Goods ſhipped out be made by any Collector, without the ſpecial Order and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Commiſſioners themſelves: And before ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can be paſſed, the Collector, upon application made unto him by the Merchant or Exporter, ſhall give a Certificate ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed joyntly by himſelf and the Cheque,<note place="margin">Upon certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate endorſed by the Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</note> expreſſing the time when the ſame were ſhipped out, and in what Parcell, the quantity and quality of the ſaid Goods, and when, and in what Parcel, and at what rate Excize had been paid for the ſame; under which Certificate, as aforeſaid, the Searcher, or elſe the Waiter, who was preſent at the ſhipping of the ſaid Goods, ſhall certifie his ſeeing the ſame done, and when, and in what Ship they were ſhipped, their quantity and quality: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter notice had and obtained that his Goods are landed or arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in any Forreign Part or Place beyond the Seas, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or Importer bringing the Certificate aforeſaid, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king due proof by Oath before the Commiſſioners, or ſuch as they ſhall appoint,<note place="margin">And Oath of the Merchant.</note> of his Goods being <hi>re verâ</hi> landed beyond the Seas, and that the Excize of the ſame had been duly paid and ſatisfied, as was expreſſed in the Certificate, ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon have Order and Warrant for repayment thereof accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in what manner to be entred in the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Books.</note>
               <hi>All Entries</hi> of Goods Outwards for beyond the Seas, (either with, or elſe without, having paid Excize) are to be Entred conſtantly by the Collector in the Day-book, drawing in that caſe a Blank Line with pricks, or otherwiſe, through the Columns for Receipts of Cuſtoms and Excize alſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34528:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS</hi> for the <hi>COLLECTORS</hi> or Sub-Commiſsioners of <hi>Excize,</hi> as to Goods ſent to, or from the Coaſt.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coaſt Goods how to be Entred.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Goods</hi> coming in from, or going out by Land or by Sea to any Port or Place of this Nation, or <hi>England,</hi> are in like manner to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and taken up, or ſhipped out by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, as is directed for the Cuſtoms. But the Merchant Importer, or Exporter, is to make Entry of the ſame by ſeverall and diſtinct Bills from thoſe he gives for the Cuſtoms, unleſſe the Merchant Importer ſhall bring in ſuch Goods which had before payed, or elſe not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly payed Excize, ſhall then happen to pay the ſame before landing, or that the Merchant Exporter ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſhip out Goods for any part of <hi>Scotland</hi> which had before paid Excize, for in theſe caſes the ſame Bills may ſerve both for Cuſtoms and Excize.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bond to be given where Goods have not paid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize.</note>
               <hi>Every Merchant</hi> ſhipping out Goods for the Coaſt which have not paid Excize, or elſe ſending ſuch Goods by Land, is in like manner as for Goods ſhipped for beyond the Seas, to give Bond or a ſufficient Obligation in Law, with condition that the Goods ſhipped out, ſhall <hi>bonâ fide</hi> be landed at ſome other Port or place of this Nation, and there Entred with the Officer appointed for receiving Excize; from whom he is to bring Certificate in due form and manner of his doing thereof,<note place="margin">To return Certificate.</note> or ſome other for him, according as by condition of his Bond is required; Which Certificate is to be returned
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34528:23"/>within ſuch convenient ſpace of time afterwards, as the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector ſhall think reaſonable for doing thereof; the ſame to be mentioned and expreſſed in the ſaid Bond, or Obligation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods having paid Excize, to be ſhipped by Sufferance.</note>
               <hi>Any Shop-keeper,</hi> Retailer, or other ſhipping out Goods, which have already paid Excize; The Collector after Entry thereof by ſuch Shop-keeper, Retailer, or other ſetting forth the quality of the Exporter, the name of the Ship, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, of whence, and to what place bound, with the quantities and qualities of his Goods, and when, and in what parcell cleared as to Excize, is to grant or permit a Sufferance for ſhipping thereof, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The form of a Permit, or Sufferance.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH</hi> Excize.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IN the</hi> Sarah <hi>of</hi> Brunt-Iſland, Anthony Lilburn <hi>Maſter, pro</hi> Inverneſſe,</p>
                  <p>Michael Craig <hi>Retailer,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two Hogſheads of <hi>French</hi> Wines but not to be Exported without further order.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector. <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Waiter, who is to ſee the goods brought from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters.</note>Which Sufferance is to be delivered to the hands of the Searcher or Waiter appointed to attend the Ship, in which the ſaid Goods ſhall be laden, who ſhall preſently go with the Exporter and ſee the ſame brought forth out of the Shop, Celler, or Ware-houſe of ſuch Exporter, and no other, and afterwards laden and ſhipped on board the Ship, or Veſſel, to which they were deſigned. All which, ſuch Searcher or Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall indorſe or certifie on the back ſide of ſuch Permit, or Sufferance, and afterward deliver the ſame back again unto the chief Searcher, or where there is none,<note place="margin">And upon cauſe of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Collector therewith, who is to try the verity by Oath.</note> unto the Collector to be kept by him and the Cheque, untill the Ship be fully la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; But if the Goods ſhall be brought or delivered out of any other place then aforeſaid, whereby ſuſpition may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of ſome fraud or colluſion, the Searcher or Waiter is to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34528:24"/>forbear ſhipping the Goods, and to inform the Collector and Cheque of the Port therewith, who are thereupon to be fully ſatisfied by the Oath of the Parties, or others, (which Oath the Collector is therefore to adminiſter to them) that the Goods have <hi>bonâ fide</hi> paid Excize, before the ſame be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be ſhipped in any Ship or Veſſel whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bill of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to be made from the ſeverall Sufferances, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>When any</hi> Ship bound outwards for the Coaſt is fully laden, the Collector or chief Searcher where there is one, from the ſeveral Sufferances, Cocquets, and Tranſires given and returned from the Waiter (for all Cocquets, Tranſires, and Sufferances for ſhipping Goods Outwards for the Coaſt, after the doing thereof, are to be returned and delivered unto the chief Searcher or Collector, as aforeſaid, (where there is no ſuch Searcher) ſhall make and (beſides all Cocquets and Tranſires granted as to the Coaſt relating to Cuſtoms) frame a true Content of the whole Ships or Veſſels Lading: which Content is to expreſſe and mention the name of the Ship, or Veſſel, with the Maſter thereof, the true Denomination, Numbers, and Marks of the Bales, Packs, Casks, outward Bulk, or Veſſels in which any Commodities are contained, and the Names of the Perſons to whom conſigned, the Net Weight, Meaſure, juſt Contents, and Values of the ſeverall Commodities, expreſſed in words at length, and not in Figures, and whether the duty of Excize be paid or no, and how much (where the ſame can be aſcertained) and when, and whether Bond be Entred into for delivery and due Entry of the Goods in the Office of Excize in the Port whither the Goods are deſigned and ſent; which Content (made according to the qualifications aforeſaid) ſhall be ſigned by the Collector and Cheque joyntly,<note place="margin">Which after ſearch of the Veſſel is to be delivered to the Maſter thereof.</note> and (after ſearch made by the Collector, or chief Searcher, where there is ſuch a Searcher, whether there be not more, or other Goods laden on Board then are ſpecified and mentioned in the ſame) ſhall be delivered unto the Maſter of ſuch Ship or Veſſel, to be by him afterwards delivered, after his arrivall in Port, unto the Sub-Commiſſioners, Collectors, or other chief Officer for Excize there.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34528:24"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ships coming from the Coaſt and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but part; the Goods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, to be endorſed on the Bill of Content.</note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon arrivall</hi> of any Ship from the Coaſt, the Collector is to call for the Maſters Bill of Contents, which is to be kept and filed with the Entry of the Ship: And when any Ship bound from one Port to another ſhall happen to deliver any part of her Goods by the way, before ſhe arrive at her laſt deſigned Port, the Sub-Commiſſioner, or Collector of the ſaid Port, is to call for the Certificate of the Content, which was delivered unto the Maſter at the Port where ſhe was laden, and certify upon the back of the ſame, what Goods are there delivered, as part of the ſaid Certificate, what remaining in the Ship, and what put on board at the Port, delivering back the ſaid Content unto the Maſter at his going thence; and keeping a Copy of his Endorſement of the ſaid Content by him, ſhall cauſe the ſame to be tranſcribed, and Entred, as all other Tickets and Certificates in the Waſte-Book.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods ſent by Land car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage upon Bond.</note>
               <hi>All Goods,</hi> and Marchandizes, ſent after Bond gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by Land Carriage unto any other Port or place, are to be ſent and paſſed by Ticket, in manner and form following.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The form of a Land carriage Ticket.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>A. B. is permitted upon Bond given, to ſend to the Burgh of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> by C. D. Carrier, being conſigned unto E. F. of the ſaid Town, or Burgh.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated, <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> Collector, <hi>C. D.</hi> Cheque.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To pay Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to a Retailer.</note>Which Ticket being received by the Collector of that place, he is in caſe the Goods therein mentioned ſhall happen to be conſigned to a Shop-keeper or Retailer of the ſame Commodity, to demand and receive Excize preſently for the ſame; but if to a known Merchant (who is purely ſuch,) then the ſame are to be Entred, Charged,<note place="margin">Or elſe charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to account of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, if to a Merchant.</note> and paſſed to his proper accompt, as if they had been then Imported by himſelf from beyond the Seas; The like to be obſerved for all Goods ſhipped by Bond for the Coaſt.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:34528:25"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The nature of the Bond.</note>Foraſmuch as Bond given in this caſe is not for payment of the duty, but for to cauſe true landing or delivering the ſame at the Port, or Place to which they are ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> carried by Land, are to be carried by Ticket di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the place unto which they are intended;<note place="margin">Goods going by Land or Water, or both, how to paſſe.</note> but all Goods going by Sea, or Water, are to paſſe no further by Ticket or Bill of Content, but to the next Port; and if to paſſe afterwards up into the Country, are to be firſt Entred with the Sub-Commiſſioner, or Collector in the ſaid Port where they are landed, and afterwards to paſſe by Ticket from him and the Cheque there unto the deſigned place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coaſt-Goods uncleared, or cleared, how to be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Books of the Collectors.</note>
               <hi>All Entries</hi> both Inwards, and Outwards, from and to the Coaſt, of Goods which had not before paid Excize, are to be duly Entred in the ſame order in which they are paſſed in the Caſh or Day-book, drawing in this caſe, a blank line through both Columns, as is directed for Goods for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas. But the Entries of all other Goods to or from the Coaſt, which had before paid Excize, are to be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Coaſt-book at the end of the reſpective Cuſtom-Entries for the ſame Goods there, with ſignification, that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize had been paid for the ſame; the date of the Certificate ſignifying ſo much, and the place whence ſuch Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate came.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Ledger to be kept.</note>To the end all Merchants may be duly Accompted with, the Collector in every Port is to prepare and keep a fair Book, or <hi>Ledger,</hi> by way of <hi>Debitor,</hi> and <hi>Creditor,</hi> in which he ſhal give every particular known Merchant within his Diſtrict or Precinct a particular and diſtinct Accompt. On the <hi>Debitor</hi> or left ſide of which Book,<note place="margin">Manner of poſting it.</note> he ſhall firſt poſt all Forraign Goods and Merchandizes found upon the hands of the particular and reſpective Merchants, at the time of the Search, and all other Goods and Merchandizes Imported at any time ſince the Twenty fourth day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, whether with, or without Bond given upon their Entry, as to Excize; And afterwards, he ſhall conſtantly every
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34528:25"/>day, or every other day at furtheſt, from the Caſh or Day-book, Poſt all Forreign Goods and Merchandizes which ſhall in like manner at any time be Imported, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from beyond the Seas, or elſe from any other Port or Place of this Nation, or elſe from <hi>England,</hi> any Port or Place thereof, without payment of the duty of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize; And on the <hi>Creditor</hi> or right ſide of the ſaid <hi>Ledger</hi> ſhall Poſt all Goods Sold, Tranſported, Exported, or ſent by Tranſire into any other Head-port, or Member thereof, upon the particular Accompt of the reſpective Merchants before Sale, either from beyond the Seas, or from any Port or place of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS</hi> to the <hi>COLLECTORS</hi> or Sub-Commiſsioners, aſwell for their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting with Merchants, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, generally relating to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Excize and Cuſtoms.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Merchants to be accompted with, every three months, or oftner.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very three Moneths</hi> conſtantly, or oftner, as ſhall be thought fit by the Collector, the Importers, according to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Act of Parliament of the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1649. are to be called upon and required to give a particular Accompt of all Goods and Merchandizes which ſhall be remaining on their hands reſpectively to that day; and in caſe of failure, or elſe after bringing in their Accompt, ſuch further Proceedings are to be had thereupon, as in the ſaid 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article is directed.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:34528:26"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How far the Collector ſhall proceed in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the <hi>25.</hi> Article.</note>And which the Collector in every particular is to purſue and execute, except to Impriſonment of any Perſon, and in caſe of proceeding to that length, the Collector (if ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is or ſhall be willing and able to give ſecurity for his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance before the Commiſſioners) ſhall ceaſe from going any further, and tranſmit the whole therefore to them who will take care to do therein as to Equity and Juſtice ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain; But if ſuch perſon is not able, or ſhall refuſe to give ſecurity as aforeſaid, the Collector ſhall proceed on to Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, (as in the before mentioned Article is directed and appointed) by Warrant to the Gaoler, or Keeper, as is uſuall, in which he ſhall alwayes mention at large his Proceſſe, and the Judgement, and his default, and the default of Diſtreſſe.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of the Summons to Accompt.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Excize Office, <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN purſuance of an Order and Declaration of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> and his Councill; Entituled, <hi>An Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe, and Councill, for Collecting of the Excize in</hi> Scotland, dated the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>May, 1655.</hi> And by vertue and according to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> paſſed the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Auguſt, 1649.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and now in force in <hi>Scotland.</hi> You are hereby required, to bring and deliver in writing, at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize Office in <hi>Leith,</hi> upon the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> next inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the date hereof, a particular Accompt of all Goods, or Merchandize this day remaining, or which ſhall remain on your hand, the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> next enſuing the date hereof, in order to the ſtating and clearing of your Accompt of Importations, from the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> to the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> next enſuing the date hereof; And you are to take notice, that if you ſhall refuſe to give in ſuch Accompt, or neglect to do the ſame, for eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes after this Warning, you will be preſently lyable to pay the whole Excize for all Goods that ſhall be found to ſtand charged in the Excize Books on your Accompt, by your
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34528:26"/>Entries at the Cuſtom-houſe, which have not otherwiſe been cleared by Sales, and deliveries, for which Tickets have been given out of this Office, and will be accordingly adjudged and warned to pay the ſame in, within fourteen dayes after, or in default thereof on your part, Warrant, of Diſtreſſe, will be iſſued againſt you for double the value of all ſuch Goods as upon your Accompt of Entries ſhall be found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining on your hands; or in default thereof, be further proceeded againſt, as in and by the ſaid Article is provided.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed> A. B. Sub-Commiſſioner.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To Maſter E. F. Merchant.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of the Summons to pay Excize after neglect of bringing in Accompt.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Excize Office, <hi>LEITH.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas in purſuance of an Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill; Entituled, <hi>An Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe, and Councill, for Collecting the Excize in</hi> Scotland, dated the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>May, 1655.</hi> And by vertue, and according to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> paſſed the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Auguſt, 1649.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and now in force in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> You were Summoned to bring and deliver in writing unto this Office, a particular Accompt of all ſuch Goods and Merchandizes which were remaining on your hands the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> which you have refuſed, or neglected to do. And whereas upon adjuſting therefore of your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts to that day, you ſtand charged in this Office by your Entries at the Cuſtom-houſe, which have not been cleared by Sales, or delivery, for which Ticket have been given out of this Office, with <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Excize of which Goods, amounts to the ſum of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> You are therefore, hereby required to bring in, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34528:27"/>pay the ſaid ſum within fourteen dayes, or otherwiſe, there will be proceſſe iſſued out againſt you, as by the ſaid Act of Parliament is appointed, and directed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>165<gap reason="blank" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>_</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>A. B. Sub-Commiſſioner.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="form">
               <body>
                  <head>The Form of the Warrant of Diſtreſſe upon failure of payment.</head>
                  <p>VVHereas <hi>E. F.</hi> in purſuance of an Order and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Highneſſe the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> and his Councill, Intituled, <hi>An Order and Declaration of his Highneſſe, and Councill, for Collecting the Excize in</hi> Scotland; dated the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of <hi>May, 1655.</hi> and by vertue, and according to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> paſſed the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Auguſt, 1649.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and now in force in <hi>Scotland;</hi> was upon the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> ſummoned to bring and deliver in writing unto this Office, a particular Accompt of all ſuch Goods and Merchandizes which were remaining on his hands the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> And foraſmuch as upon his refuſall, or neglect in doing thereof, the ſaid <hi>E. F.</hi> having his Accompt adjuſted, was found to ſtand charged in this Office by his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries at the Cuſtom-houſe, (which have not been cleared by Sales, or deliveries, for which Tickets have been given out of this Office) with <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> was upon the day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> required, and injoyned within fourteen dayes following, to pay and ſatisfie the Excize of the ſaid Goods, which doth amount to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> And the ſaid <hi>E F.</hi> having nevertheleſſe failed in doing thereof; Theſe are therefore to Authorize you, and every of you, to repair unto the dwelling houſe of the ſaid <hi>E. F.</hi> and therein, or in any other place belonging to the ſaid <hi>E. F.</hi> to ſeize, diſtrain, and carry away ſo much of his Goods, and Chattels, as may ſufficiently ſatisfie the ſum of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> being double the value of the Goods aforeſaid, which he hath forfeited, according to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of the <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34528:27"/>
                     <hi>mentioned, for his neglect and refuſall, as aforeſaid. And all Officers, aſwell Military as Civill, are hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively prayed and required to be aiding and aſſiſting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in the due execution hereof, according as is directed and appointed in that behalf. Dated the &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. B. <hi>Sub-Commiſſioner.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And if Return be made, that no Diſtreſſe can be found or had, the Collector is then to proceed to certifie the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, or otherways to do, as is directed before.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All moneys to be received openly.</note>
               <hi>ALL moneys</hi> paid or received for Excize or Cuſtoms, ſhall be paid and received, not privatly, but openly in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom-houſe, or in the place appointed for Receipts of the ſame, and that in the preſence of the Cheque; And all moneys are to be entred to accompt preciſely upon the very day upon which it is Received; And if not,<note place="margin">And placed to account the ſame day it is received.</note> the ſame to be holden and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Diſtinct Entryes and Payments, and to be made good in Accompt as ſuch, by the Collector and Sub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Books to be carried out of the Office.</note>
               <hi>All Buſineſs</hi> of: Excize and Cuſtoms, ſhall be openly and publickly tranſacted and performed in the Publick Office, and no Books of the ſame ſhall at any time be kept or carried out of the ſame, for, or upon any occaſion whatſoever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpeciall direction of the Commiſſioners, or the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor Generall in that behalf.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Entries of Excize how to be filed and kept.</note>
               <hi>All Entries</hi> relating to the Excize and Cuſtoms, ſhall be filed together in the Order of their Dates and Paſſing, to be kept, duly numbred &amp; bundled in bundles; containing four months Entries, or Bills together, to begin from the firſt of <hi>October,</hi> 1655. <hi>incluſivè,</hi> and ſo for every four months following ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively to be kept; the Entries Inwards for Excize of Goods from beyond the Seas by themſelves; the Entries Outwards from beyond the Seas by themſelves; The Entries Inwards for the Coaſt for Goods, which have not paid Excize, by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34528:28"/>And thoſe Outwards to the Coaſt for like Goods, by themſelves; The Entryes Inwards and Outwards, from and to the Coaſt, for Goods which have paid the ſame, by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; The Bills of Content, and Bills of Sale or Entryes of the ſame, diſtinct and apart by themſelves, and the like to be done by all Entries for Cuſtoms,<note place="margin">All Bonds taken, to be ſent to the Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers forthwith. All Bonds to be taken, to be ſent every three months.</note> Inwards and Outwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Bonds</hi> already taken, for, or by reaſon of, or relating to Excize either Inwards or Outwards, or for any other cauſe whatſoever, are forthwith to be tranſmitted and ſent unto the Commiſſioners at the Cuſtom-houſe in <hi>Leith;</hi> And all other hereafter to be entred into, and taken, ſhall every three Months in like manner, or oftner, be ſent unto them, to be afterwards delivered up, or tranſmitted unto the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, as to Equity and Juſtice ſhall appertain.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Collector where there is no Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, is to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate as ſuch.</note>The Sub-Commiſſioners, or Collectors, reſpectively in every Port, where there is no Chief Searcher, is, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> to do all and every Act and Acts, Thing and Things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, directed and appointed to be done, in and by his the ſaid Searcher his Inſtructions hereafter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34528:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS</hi> For the Chief Searcher in the Port of Leith, &amp;c.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">He is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Collector with all Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and going out.</note>1.<hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>irſt, you</hi> are diligently to attend the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of your Truſt, and upon notice had of any Ship coming in with Goods and Merchandize, forthwith to acquaint the Collector of <hi>Leith</hi> (or other Head-Port where you ſhall be, and under which ſuch Veſſell ſhall lye, therewith) who is to appoint a Waiter to attend on Board, whom you ſhall cauſe to enter on Board ſuch Ship, and there to remain untill ſuch time as ſuch Ship ſhall be brought unto the Haven or Key, and there delivered.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Take care no Goods be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or ſhipped without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note>II. <hi>You are</hi> to take care, That no Goods, Wares or Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize be unladen out of, or laden on Board any Ship, or other Veſſell whatſoever, either Inwards or Outwards bound, without due Entry firſt made, both as to Cuſtoms and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, and due Warrant obtained and granted from the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Cheque for the unlading or ſhipping off of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>You are,</hi> according to the beſt of your power, skill and knowledge,<note place="margin">Inſtruct the Waiters how to enter and indorſe their Warrants.</note> to direct the ſeverall Waiters imployed in the Port of <hi>Leith</hi> and Members thereof, or any other the Ports reſpectively, within the Limits and Precincts of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; And to ſee that every Waiter reſpectively, do enter into a Book, the day of the going out and coming in of every
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34528:29"/>Ship, unto which he ſhall be appointed to attend, with the name of the Ship and Maſter, and the date of every mans Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, Warrant or Certificate, as they in order of the dayes of every Moneth ſhall fall out, the particular Quantities, Lengths, Weights, Meaſures, Numbers and Marks of all and every the Goods, Wares or Merchandize, which every or any ſuch Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be appointed to ſee unladen or laden, from, or on board any Ship or Veſſell whatſoever, with the time when, and to, and by whom the ſame were delivered or ſhipped out; And alſo to take care, that the reſpective Waiters do likeways indorſe the ſeverall particulars upon the back of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive VVarrants, which they ſhall receive for landing or lading of Goods, and return them ſo entred unto your ſelf, before any Ship Inwards and Outwards be fully cleared, or permitted to go away and be diſcharged.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Keep the Skippers books.</note>IV. <hi>You are</hi> in the <hi>Skippers Books,</hi> Inwards and Outwards, enter every Ship, coming in, and going out, by way of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, the Name of the Ship, and the Maſter, her burden, or whence,<note place="margin">Enter all Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels therein, before lading or unlading.</note> and to, or from what place ſhe is come, or bound, and the name of the VVaiter appointed to attend ſuch Ship, before ſuch Maſter be permitted to diſcharge, or lade, or take in any Goods, VVares and Merchandize whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Take the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Report</note>V. <hi>You are</hi> to demand and receive from the Maſter or Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of every Ship Inwards, a Report or Bill of Content of the particular Lading of every ſuch Veſſell, with the Names of the ſeverall Merchants, and the Mark, Number, Package, and Outward form of the Goods and Merchandize; which Bill of Contents is to be verified by the Oath of ſuch Maſter or Purſer,<note place="margin">And Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</note> in preſence of your ſelf and Cheque, or elſe of the Collector and Cheque, who is alſo to declare upon his ſaid Oath, whether he hath broke Bulk or no, ſince he came into the Port, or any other the Ports of this Nation, otherways than in the ſaid Bill of Contents ſhall be mentioned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; and if ſo, then what and where ſuch Goods were
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34528:29"/>delivered, and to whom belonging or conſigned; And further, to make anſwer to all ſuch Queſtions concerning Goods laden in the ſaid Ship, as ſhall be reaſonably demanded of him; The like <hi>Mutatis Mutandis</hi> is to be done and practized with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Maſter of a Ship outwards, before he be ſuffered to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of Harbour, or receive his Cocquets, Tranſires, Bills of Content, or other Tickets or VVarrants,<note place="margin">And enter them.</note> either as to Cuſtoms or Excize: And all Reports and Examinations taken as aforeſaid, are to be entred in the Skippers Books Inwards or Outwards, unto which they ſhall relate reſpectively.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>You are</hi> to be carefull and ſee,<note place="margin">Jerk.</note> that every Ship Inwards or Outwards, be duly Jerked, by comparing the Reſpective Bills of Contents of every Ship Inwards or Outwards, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective VVarrants returned by the VVaiter or VVaiters for every ſuch Ships, unto the lading or unlading, whereof he or they were appointed: And if the ſame agree, and that every ſuch Ship be fully Entred, to ſuffer the ſame to be diſcharged, or go. But you are firſt to go on board ſuch Ship, and ſearch, ſee and ſurvey,<note place="margin">Search all Ships, and ſeize pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and uncuſtomed Goods.</note> whether there be no Goods yet left concealed on board, which have not been Entred Inwards; or whether there have not any other or more Goods been ſhipped on board any Ship Outwards, then ſuch onely for which VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or Sufferance hath been granted. And in caſe you find any Goods concealed, hid or ſhipt out, as aforeſaid, or being prohibited, or uncuſtomed Goods, you are to ſeize and bring the ſame away unto the Publick VVare-houſe of the Cuſtom-houſes, or ſome other convenient place adjoyning, where they may be moſt conveniently ſecured, and forthwith to acquaint the Commiſſioners or Collectors therewith.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>You are</hi> after the Jerking of any Ship, to annex or file to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the VVaiters Bills,<note place="margin">File the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Reports and Waiters Bils after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of them.</note> and the reſpective Bills of Contents formerly given in, as aforeſaid, by any Skipper or Purſer, and numbering the VVaiters Bills in Order of their Dates, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Number of the ſaid Bills in words at length, at the bottom of the Maſters or Purſers Bill of Content, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34528:30"/>examining the ſame with the Caſh or Day-Book, and finding them to agree, to file them all together, and lay them up in ſome convenient place, to be produced upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>You ſhall</hi> be diligent and carefull, to make ſtay, or cauſe to be made ſtay,<note place="margin">Make ſtay of all Goods brought in, ſhipped out, or delivered, contrary to the Law of Cuſtom or Excize.</note> of all Goods, Wares and Merchandize prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to be brought in, or carryed out and delivered, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be carryed in, or out of this Nation, or the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, or delivered to any buyer of the ſame, contrary to any Act, Ordinances, Orders or Declarations, as well of his Highneſſe and Councill, as of Parliament, which are in force both touching Cuſtoms and Excize.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>You are</hi> at all times, and as often as you ſhall ſee cauſe, or have juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion,<note place="margin">Go on board to ſearch,</note> to go on board any Ship, or other Veſſels riding in Harbour, or in any Road, within the Precincts or Limits aforeſaid, to ſee, ſurvey and ſearch for all manner of Goods prohibited or uncuſtomed, which you are to ſeize or bring away, as aforeſaid: And further, with the conſent and directions of the Collector,<note place="margin">And enter Waiters.</note> to put any Waiter he ſhall appoint, on board any Ship riding in the Road, who is to remain there, and come in with ther, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch Ship be cleared and diſcharged.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>You are</hi> to take care,<note place="margin">See to the Waiters at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance,</note> that the ſeverall Waiters appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to attend any Ships, or otherways, at <hi>Leith</hi> or <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> do conſtantly and duely give their attendance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. And that ſuch of them who ſhall have no particular charge at any time, do conſtantly attend ſome at the Shoar, and ſome at the Ports of <hi>Leith</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh,</hi> for the making ſtay of all Goods,<note place="margin">At ſhoar and Ports.</note> which ſhall not be duely entred, or elſe delivered by the Merchant, to any the buyers thereof, without any Ticket or Warrant, as to the Excize.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:34528:30"/> XI. <hi>And becauſe</hi> in time of Trade,<note place="margin">Cauſe them to watch.</note> much fraud is uſually practiſed and uſed, you are at any time, when you finde ſtore of ſhipping in Harbour, to appoint one or more of the Waiters, by turns each night, to watch along the ſhoar of the Haven, and to ſeize any Goods landed at unlawfull hours.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">Acquaint the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with their neglects.</note>XII. <hi>You are</hi> from time to time to acquaint the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with any the Omiſſions, Neglects, or other failures of all, or any the Waiters.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. <hi>You are</hi> to obſerve, purſue and follow in all things, the ſeverall Acts, Ordinances, Orders and Declarations,<note place="margin">And obſerve theſe and all other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions given him.</note> as well of his Highneſſe and Councill, as of Parliament, touching Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize and Cuſtoms. And in all things, honeſtly and faithfully to demean your ſelf according to your Commiſſion, Theſe and all other Inſtructions which you ſhall receive from the Commiſſioners, or their Surveyor-Generall from time to time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34528:31"/>
            <head>INSTRUCTIONS <hi>For the</hi> WAITERS.</head>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall</hi> give your faithfull and diligent attendance in the Port or Place where you ſhall be appointed and directed to attend as Waiter,<note place="margin">To attend di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently.</note> and give notice to the Collector or chief Searcher (where there is ſuch a Searcher) of that Port with all convenient ſpeed,<note place="margin">Give notice of all Ships co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, or going out.</note> of every Ship that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in, or goeth out every Tide by way of Merchandize, or with any Goods from, or to any Forreign Parts, or from, or to any Port of this Nation, or of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>You are</hi> forthwith upon warrant or other direction given from the Collector and Searcher,<note place="margin">Board or wait on Ships in lading.</note> to enter on board any Ship or Veſſel, and there to remain untill ſhe be fully diſcharged and delivered: And to ſee unto the ſhipping of all Goods Outwards, unto which you ſhall at any time in like manner be directed and appointed.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>You ſhall</hi> not permit or ſuffer any Goods, Wares or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize to be unladen out,<note place="margin">Suffer no Goods to be landed or ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, without the Duties firſt paid.</note> nor laden on board of any Ship or Veſſel, either inwards or Outwards, before due Entry made of the ſame with the Collector of the Port in or out of which any Goods ſhall be brought or ſhipped out, and all duties du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid and ſatisfied, aſwell of Cuſtoms as Excize, where Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize ſhall be due and payable.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:34528:31"/> IV. <hi>You are</hi> upon the unlading of any Goods,<note place="margin">Nor more Goods than ſhall be entred.</note> to take care that no more, or other Goods either for quantity or quality, be unladen and delivered, then are mentioned in the Warrant you ſhall receive from the Collector and Cheque; And where you ſhall find Goods ſhort entred (if the ſame exceed not Twenty <hi>per Cent.</hi> in which the Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowed unto the Merchant, is to be included in the quantity thereof, in proportion with the Goods mentioned in your Warrant) you are to make ſtay of,<note place="margin">If ſo, or that the Goods be landed at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful time or place, to ſeize them.</note> or bring the overplus unto the Warehouſe of the Cuſtom-houſe, there to remain untill the Merchant do make a Poſt-Entry of the ſame: But if the Goods exceed the quantity aforeſaid, or landed at unlawfull time or place, or without the privity of the Officer, properly concerned for the doing thereof, you are to ſeize the ſame, and to acquaint the Collector and Cheque therewith.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>You are</hi> not to permit or ſuffer any Ballaſt,<note place="margin">Not to ſuffer Ballaſt, or any thing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to be ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped without Warrant.</note> Proviſion of Victuals, or any other Goods or Things whatſoever, although paying no Duties, to be put on board any Ship whatſoever, without particular Warrant from the Collector and Cheque for doing thereof. And upon the ſhipping off of any Goods or Merchandize, you are to examine and ſee that all Goods ſhipped off do agree in quantity,<note place="margin">Nor more, or leſſe than is contained in ſuch Warrant, without ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting the Collector or Searcher therewith.</note> quality, weight, number and meaſure, with the Warrant you ſhall receive, and that neither more or leſſe be laden on board than is therein mentioned and expreſſed; and if more, you are to make ſeizure of the ſame; but if leſſe, you are to acquaint the Collector and Cheque, or Searcher therewith, before the Ship on which ſuch Goods ſhall be laden ſhall be permitted to go forth.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>You are</hi> upon the landing and ſhipping off of all Goods, to receive a Warrant for doing thereof,<note place="margin">To have War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant aſwel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize as Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</note> aſwel relating to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize as Cuſtoms. And wherever Excize is due to be paid upon the importing or landing any Goods, you are not to ſuffer the ſame to be carried away, before the Excize, aſwell as Cuſtoms, be paid and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:34528:32"/> VII. <hi>Whenever</hi> any Shop-keeper,<note place="margin">To ſee al goods ſhipped out by Shopkeepers to be brought im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly from their ſhops <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</note> Retailer, or other perſon ſhall export any Goods, you are to ſee that the ſame be brought from the known or common reputed Houſe, Shop or Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of ſuch Shop keeper, Retailer or other, and not from any other Houſe or Place whatſoever; And if ſo, you are not to ſuffer the ſame to be laden on board, before you ſhall have firſt acquainted the Collector or chief Searcher therewith, and received ſuch further Order therein as the nature and occaſion of the affair ſhall require.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. You are conſtantly in a Book,<note place="margin">To keep a book and therein to enter all goods taken up and ſhipped off by Warrant, &amp;c</note> to be made and kept for that purpoſe, to enter the day of the coming in, and going out of every Ship, unto the unlading, or lading whereof you ſhall be appointed to attend, with the Name of the Ship or Maſter; and under each reſpective Ship, as aforeſaid, either coming in, or going out, you ſhall enter the date of every Warrant, Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, Tranſire, or Certificate (according to the order of their dates) which you ſhall receive for the landing and taking on ſhore, or ſhipping of any Goods, together with the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, qualities, numbers, weights, meaſures, and marks of all and every the Wares, Goods and Merchandize which ſhall be delivered on ſhore, or ſhipped upon any ſuch Warrant, Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, Tranſire or Certificate, with the time when, and how much at a time of the ſame was ſo landed or ſhipped out, and by whom the ſame were taken up and ſhipped off, and to what place, or unto whoſe Cellar or Warehouſe (as near as poſſible you can find) Goods ſo taken up were carried and houſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter landing.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>You are</hi> after the execution of any Warrant,<note place="margin">To endorſe the Warrants, and deliver them afterward to the Collector or Searcher.</note> Cocquet, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or Certificate either Inwards or Outwards, to endorſe (and afterwards ſubſcribe your hand to) the ſeverall parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars before-mentioned, on the backſide of the reſpective Warrants, by which any Goods were landed or ſhipped, and preſently thereupon to deliver back ſuch Warrants into the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34528:32"/>hands of the chief Searcher, (where there is ſuch a one) or elſe of the Collector in that Port to diſpoſe thereof, according as they are directed and appointed.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>You are</hi> to take notice of no <hi>Outs</hi> upon the Importation of any Wines,<note place="margin">What Outs ſhall be noted.</note> unleſſe the ſame be ſhewn unto you on ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, after plucking the ſame out of the Hold, and before the laying the ſame on ſhore.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. <hi>You are</hi> upon juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion,<note place="margin">To ſearch or ſeize Uncuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited Goods.</note> to enter on board any Ship or Veſſel aſwell by night as by day, riding, lying or being within any the ſeveral Ports, Havens, Creeks or other places; As alſo in the day-time to go and enter into any Houſe, Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, or Cellar, or other place whatſoever, and therein to ſee, ſurvey and make ſearch for any prohibited or unacuſtomed Goods, and the ſame to ſeize, and bring, or cauſe to be brought into the Publick Warehouſe of the Cuſtom-houſe, there to remain untill due proceedings at Law may be had thereupon.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. <hi>Where any</hi> Goods,<note place="margin">To ſeize all Goods delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without Ticket.</note> Wares or Merchandize ſhall be delivered from any Merchant unto any Buyer thereof, either without payment of Excize, Ticket or Warrant, or where more or other Goods, either for quantity or quality, than what ſhall be mentioned and expreſſed in any Ticket, or Bill of Sufferance,<note place="margin">Or more then mentioned in any Ticket.</note> or other Warrant for Excize ſhall be delivered by any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, or other, unto any other perſon whatſoever, you are to ſeize and ſecure the ſame.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. <hi>All Goods,</hi> Wares and Merchandize excizable, either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſold, or ſold; or which have already paid the duty of Excize,<note place="margin">To ſeize all Goods roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged without Warrant,</note> which ſhall be removed, romaged, carried, or conveyed from one place to another, without Ticket or Warrant for doing thereof; you are to ſeize and cauſe to be brought into the Publick Warehouſe of the Cuſtom-houſe,<note place="margin">Except bought from a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer.</note> unleſſe the ſame ſhall appear to be either Goods bought in a ſmall quantity, and coming from the Houſe or Shop of a Retailer thereof, or elſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34528:33"/>Goods bought by a Shop-keeper or Retailer, from another Shop-keeper or Retailer of the ſame Burgh or Town, and paſſing to his Houſe or Shop of the ſame Burgh or Town.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. <hi>You ſhall</hi> ſeize,<note place="margin">To ſeize and inform of all Goods any wayes landed, ſhipped or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize.</note> ſtay and ſecure all Goods, Wares, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize which you ſhall find to be landed, ſhipped, carried, concealed, conveyed, removed, ſold or delivered reſpectively, contrary to any Act or Ordinance, aſwell of his Highneſſe and Council, as of Parliament, for, or touching either Cuſtoms or Excize, now in force in <hi>Scotland;</hi> or upon notice or intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence had or received of any Act, or Acts, Thing, or Things, done, committed or acted contrary thereunto, ſhall inform and give notice thereof, either unto the Commiſſioners, or the Collector of the Port where you ſhall be appointed Waiter, that ſuch courſe and order may be taken therein, as of right belongeth.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. You ſhall readily do and execute every Thing and Things, as the Collector or chief Searcher (where there is one) ſhall appoint and direct,<note place="margin">To obſerve all Directions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by order of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners.</note> and diligently and faithfully to obſerve all ſuch Rules and Inſtructions as are already, or ſhall hereafter be given unto you by the Commiſſioners themſelves, the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor-General, Collector, or any other by their Order and Appointment: And further to do and officiate in all things, as the Collector himſelf may or ought to do when, and in caſe you ſhall be ſent to attend in any Member-Port, where by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of diſtance of place, the Merchant cannot poſſibly enter with the Collector in the Head-Port of that Diſtrict; But in this particular,<note place="margin">And to offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate as Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector in any Member-Port unto which he ſhall happen to be commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</note> you are to proceed no further than as the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector ſhall direct and give order unto you, by Commiſſion under his Hand and Seal; to whom you are at all times, and from time to time, to make, give, and render an Accompt of all your actions and proceedings therein.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34528:33"/>
            <head>DIRECTIONS TOUCHING <hi>SEIZ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES or DEMISES,</hi> as to CUSTOMS and EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIZE conjunctly.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Officer</hi> who ſhall make any Seizure or Demiſe of any Goods,<note place="margin">All Seizure both of Cuſtoms and Excize, to be ſignified to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zures at <hi>Leith.</hi>
               </note> or Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, as prohibited and uncuſtomed, or Imported, ſold, delivered, removed, or delivered contrary to the Laws of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, ſhall thereupon with all poſſible ſpeed acquaint the Commiſſioners of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and Excize therewith, and likewiſe certifie the ſame to the Regiſter of Seizures in the Port of <hi>Leith,</hi> for the time being, that they may be by him duly entred, and recorded, and brought to tryall, either before the Judges of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, or elſe the Commiſſioners aforeſaid, according as the nature and quality of the Seizure ſhall require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such Officer</hi> is withall to certifie unto the ſaid Regiſter,<note place="margin">All circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the ſeizure to be certified.</note> together with the quantity, and quality of Goods ſeized, the time when, and ground whereupon he ſeized or demiſed the ſame, with ſuch other circumſtances as are fit to be known for exhibiting, and forming a due Information againſt the ſame, either in the Exchequer, or before the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:34528:34"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>In caſe</hi> any Proprietor of any Goods ſeized,<note place="margin">Goods (upon licence to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound) to be Apprized.</note> or demized, procure a Licence to compound for the ſame; the Officer before he treat or compound thereupon, is to cauſe the ſaid Goods to be apprized, by vertue of a warrant of Apprizement, out of the Exchequer; which Writ, the Solicitor ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure at the requeſt and charge of the ſaid Officer, and ſend the ſame to the ſaid Officer with all ſpeed; and the Officer thereupon having cauſed the ſaid Goods to be apprized, is forthwith to return the ſame Writ (with the Indenture of Apprizement thereunto annexed) unto the Regiſter, to be by him regiſtred, and afterwards returned unto the Exchequer, in order to further proſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be leſſe then one third of the value.</note>
               <hi>For the</hi> preventing of all fraud in Compoſitions, no Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer is by vertue of any ſuch Licence, to compound for his part, at any leſſe rate, then the one third part of the whole, according as the ſaid Goods are apprized, unleſſe the ſaid Commiſſioners (being firſt acquainted therewith) do give other directions in the caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Seizour to certifie and endorſe bis compoſition.</note>After ſuch Officer hath made his Compoſition, he is forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to certifie the Collector of the Port whereunto he doth belong, what he hath, or is to receive by way of Compoſition, for his part, for the Goods ſo ſiezed or demiſed as aforeſaid; and for any charge of Intelligence, or otherwiſe by him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed about the ſame: And ſhall in the preſence of the ſaid Collector, endorſe upon the ſaid Licence in words at length, and not in figures, what the ſame amounteth unto, in one entire ſum, and ſubſcribe his name thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it to the Regiſter.</note>
               <hi>Such Officer</hi> is forthwith to return the ſame Licence, ſo endorſed to the ſaid Regiſter, to be by him regiſtred and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Exchequer, and then to be kept by him, untill ſome ſeaſonable opportunity be offered, whereby the Officer may take his Oath in a legall way, according to what is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed and ſubſcribed as aforeſaid; and that the ſaid Officer do then likewiſe return unto the ſaid Regiſter the Money for charges expended in the Exchequer in that ſuit,<note place="margin">With the charges of ſuit.</note> upon intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from him what the ſaid charges are.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:34528:34"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods ſeized not to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered till the States part, and Cuſtoms, and Excize, ſhall be paid.</note>
               <hi>Such Officer</hi> having made his Compoſition, is not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver, nor ſuffer to be delivered, ſuch Goods out of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, untill the States part of ſuch Compoſition, as alſo the Cuſtoms (and Excize, where Excize ſhall be due for the ſame) be paid to the Collector of the Port, for the uſe of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Security to be given for ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Fine.</note>
               <hi>In all</hi> and every ſuch caſes, the Collector of the Port is to take good ſecurity, or a greater ſum of money then the charges of the Exchequer, in rating the Fine, and ſuing out the <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> will amount to of the Proprietor before his Goods be delivered, with condition to procure his Fine to be forthwith rated, that ſo all other proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon may enſue; whereby the Officer may be legally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of his Seizure upon Record, and in default thereof, to leave the ſaid ſum depoſited.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Seizour to pay in the States movetie within Twenty dayes.</note>
               <hi>When any</hi> Goods ſeized, are, or ſhall be condemned in the Exchequer, the Officer (to whom the benefit thereof doth accrue) is within Twenty dayes after ſuch Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inrolled in the Exchequer, and certified unto him by the ſaid Regiſter, to pay unto the Collector, the moyetie due unto the State, according as they are apprized, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with certifie the ſaid Regiſter of the payment thereof; and is alſo to make return unto the ſaid Regiſter of the charges expended in the Exchequer by reaſon of the ſaid ſuit, being firſt made acquainted by the ſaid Regiſter what the ſaid charges are.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Goods ſeized, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Writs of delivery, to be detained till all duties be paid. Seizures where to be ſecured.</note>
               <hi>No Officer</hi> whatſoever is to deliver any Goods from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seizure, by vertue of any Writ of delivery, untill the Cuſtoms and Excize (where Excize ſhall be due) be paid to the Collector of ſuch Port, for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Goods</hi> ſeized by any the Officers of the out-Ports, are to be brought in to the States Warehouſe, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch Port, where there is any, and in caſe there be none, then into ſuch other place as the Collector ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point for ſecuring thereof, untill they be condemned, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe legally diſcharged.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:34528:35"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Collectors to take care Goods ſeized, be truly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued.</note>
               <hi>The Collectors</hi> of the ſeverall Ports are to take ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care, that upon all Apprizements made of Goods ſeized, the ſame be truely valued, and that they receive Cuſtom and Excize, in all caſes of Compoſition of any Goods; And, upon forfeiture of any Goods, if they ſhal ſee and judge it moſt for the Commonwealths advantage, then, and in ſuch caſe they may take the moyetie of ſuch Goods in kinde, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with acquaint the Commiſſioners therewith, to the end they may receive direction therein, for the Sale thereof.<note place="margin">And receive the States part in kind, or otherwiſe, as he ſhall think fit.</note> And therefore, all perſons making ſeizure before diſpoſition be by them made of any part of the Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize by them ſeized in the ſeverall Ports, are to acquaint the Collector of that Port, where ſuch ſeizure is, or ſhall be made, therewith, to know whether they will take the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths moyetie, in kinde, or not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <head>
               <hi>INSTRUCTIONS</hi> To the <hi>COLLECTORS</hi> of Cuſtoms and Excize conjunctly, touching their Moneys and Accompts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the fore-going Inſtructions, the Work and Method of the Accompts to be kept, made and done,<note place="margin">Collectors Books, viz.</note> both for Cuſtoms and Excize, is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and plain; but yet for the more Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity and clearneſſe of things, the Collector, as a <hi>Summary</hi> of the whole, if to take notice that he is to frame and keep,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>One Caſh</hi> or <hi>Day-Book,</hi> which having two ſeveral Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns, the one for Moneys received for Cuſtoms,<note place="margin">The Caſh, or Day book.</note> and the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34528:35"/>other of Moneys received for Excize, is for the making Entry therein of <hi>All Goods</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paying</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cuſtoms</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Exciſe upon</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Inwards.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Outwards.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Importation.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Sale.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Going <hi>out for beyond the Seas, either before, or after payment of Excize.</hi> Coming <hi>from</hi> England, <hi>or the Coaſt, before payment of the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With their reſpective Values and Rates, and the Product of them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Two Books</hi> for Entry of Ships,<note place="margin">Skippers Books.</note> and the Report of the Skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Inwards and Outwards.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>One Book</hi> for entry, not only of all Certificats from,<note place="margin">The Coaſt Book.</note> or to the Coaſt for Cuſtoms, but of all Goods likewiſe both Inwards and Outwards, from, or to <hi>England,</hi> or the Coaſt, which have paid Excize before ſuch their coming in, or going out.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>A Ledger,</hi> or Book of Accompt for Excize only, to be kept with all Merchants and Importers,<note place="margin">The Ledger.</note> making their Accompt <hi>Debitor</hi> for the Quantities, Weights and Meaſures of all Goods imported (the ſame to be poſted from the Day-Book, according to the Cuſtom Entries, with reference in the <hi>Led<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to the Folio of the ſaid Day-Book, and in the Day-Book to the Folio of the <hi>Ledger</hi> where the ſaid Entry is poſted) And <hi>Creditor</hi> by Sales, Allowances, and Exports, to be poſted in like manner from the ſame Book reſpectively.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>A Waſt-Book</hi> to be kept for the Entring of all Tickets that ſhall be given for all Goods which ſhall have paid Excize be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their being ſent unto any Port, Burgh,<note place="margin">The Waſte-Book.</note> Town or Place from out of the Port or Place where the ſame had paid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34528:36"/>or elſe were lying before the removal or carrying thence of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Two fair Books,</hi> firſt of which is, for the Entring (on the one ſide thereof) all Bonds which ſhall be taken,<note place="margin">The Bond Books.</note> as to Excize, upon the Importation or landing of any Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize; and on the other, all Bonds given upon the ſhipping out of any Goods excizable unto any Port of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> or any Part beyond the Seas, in the order of their dates and times in which they are taken from, or given by the Merchants. And the ſecond of them, for entring all Bonds taken in relation to the Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collectors monthly to deliver Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts, Of Moneys received.</note>THE Collector in every Port is monthly to deliver in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Commiſſioners at the Cuſtom-houſe in <hi>Leith,</hi> the ſeveral Abſtracts or Accompts following; <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of all Moneys which have been received for Cuſtoms and Excize in his respective Port, and the Members thereof, the Moneth preceding, under the ſeveral and diſtinct Heads, as followeth,</hi> Viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cuſtoms</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Excize upon</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Inwards.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Outwards.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Importation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sale.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Of Ships co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, or going out of Port.</note>II. <hi>Of what Ships or Veſſels come in, or go out of his Port, or any the Members thereof, with an Accompt of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Ladings, with the Names of the ſaid Ships or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, their Maſters, together with the Place from whence they come, or whither bound or fraighted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Of Goods ſhipped for England.</note>III. <hi>Of what Goods, Wares and Merchandize excizable, as have the Moneth preceding been exported or ſhipped out of his Port, or any the Members thereof, to any the Ports of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and therein to expreſſe the Name of the Maſter, Ship and Veſſel in which the ſame were ſhipped, together with the Names of the Perſons entring the ſame Outwards, with the quantity and quality of the Goods ſo entred; and whether they were paſſed (as to Excize) upon Bond, or otherwiſe, after payment of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:34528:36"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All Money to be entred to Accompt of the ſame day upon which they ſhall be received.</note>All Moneys received for Cuſtoms or Excize, or both, are to be entred in his Caſh or day-Book preciſely, upon the ſame day upon which the ſame was paid and received: And in caſe Moneys received on one day ſhall happen to be entred or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted for on another day, the ſame is to be reputed and eſteemed two ſeveral Sums of Money, which the Collector is therefore to make good &amp; pay into the Commonwealth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. The ſame courſe to be obſerved in Entry of Goods.</p>
            <p>No Collector is to give any truſt or forbearance to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoever, for or in reſpect either of Cuſtoms,<note place="margin">No truſt or forbearance to be given.</note> Excize, Seizure or Fines, but at their own perils; Except with Licence of the Commiſſioners, or in caſes of Sufferance, mentioned in the 21<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of the <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> of the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1649. Provided alwayes, that the time therein limited, be not exceeded without proceeding, as by the ſaid Article, and ſome of the preceding Inſtructions, is directed and appointed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collectors, or Sub-commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt every four months.</note>
               <hi>At the end</hi> and expiration of every four Moneths, to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned and begin from the firſt of <hi>October,</hi> 1655, <hi>incluſive,</hi> every Collector or Sub-Commiſſioner is to cloſe and ſhut up his Accompt (and ſo for every four Moneths following) upon the laſt day of the ſaid four Moneths preciſely, and what ever Money ſhall be received after that day is to be brought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in its proper place, and on the ſame day on which it was received; and within ten dayes at furtheſt after the term and expiration of every four Moneths, as aforeſaid, he is to ſend and deliver to the Commiſſioners a true, perfect and particular Accompt Of all
<list>
                  <item>Subſidy and Cuſtome</item>
                  <item>Excize
<list>
                        <item>Paid and received</item>
                        <item>for Goods
<list>
                              <item>Paid and received Inwards.</item>
                              <item>Paid and received Outwards.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>upon
<list>
                              <item>Importation.</item>
                              <item>Sale.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list> Together with an Abſtract of the ſaid four Moneths, in the ſame manner and form with that given before monthly; And at the end of all an Accompt currant, therein making himſelf <hi>Debitor</hi> for the Moneys received, and <hi>Creditor</hi> by all ſuch
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34528:37"/>Moneys as he hath paid into the Treaſury, or elſe returned by Bill, that ſo it may appear whether the whole be paid in, or how much thereof is remaining unpaid.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To ſend up a Tranſcript of all Tickets received.</note>
               <hi>And together</hi> with the four Moneths Books of Accompt, aforeſaid, the Collector in every Port is to ſend up a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of all Tickets received for any Goods coming into his Port, or any the Members thereof, by Land or Water from any other Port or Place either of this Nation, or elſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And beſides, to keep and frame, and ſo ſend and deliver in monthly (and afterwards every four Moneths) an Accompt diſtinct and apart by it ſelf,<note place="margin">An accompt of all Fines and Seizures.</note> of all Moneys and other Goods and things received, had, and taken for Seizures, Fines, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures and Penalties, for, or relating either to Cuſtoms or Excize, with an Accompt currant thereof, how, and in what manner paid, either into the Treaſury, or elſe the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers according to the Laws of Excize in that behalf. The manner and form of all which Accompts, every Collector, for his better Information, ſhall receive herewith, and therefore will be left without excuſe, in caſe any ſhould fail of his, or their duties herein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collectors and ſub-Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their Moneys monethly, and to clear and pay every four Moneths Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt at the time of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering in of their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts.</note>
               <hi>Neither</hi> will it be ſufficient deſcribed before, ſhould within ten dayes at the furtheſt, after the end and expiration of every four Moneths, be delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Commiſſioners at <hi>Leith;</hi> but it is likewiſe expected that the Collectors, imbracing all opportunity and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of making and paying in their Moneys monthly (which they ſhall receive) unto Mr. <hi>Anthony Wilſon</hi> Treaſurer at <hi>Leith,</hi> will and do not fail to have all ſuch Moneys, as ſhall be due and payable at the end of every four Moneths, upon their reſpective Accompts, either in a readineſſe to be paid (or elſe actually paid) in, at, or before the giving in of their Accompts reſpectively for the full ballancing and clearing of the ſame, as he or they eſteem the Repute of being accountd diligent and faithfull, and thereby avoid all ſuch inconveniences, as well or may otherwiſe happen and fall upon the Contraveners here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="penalties">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34528:37"/>
            <head>A COLLECTION Of the ſeverall Fines, Penalties and Forfeitures ſet and impoſed, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Cuſtoms and Excize reſpectively, by the ſeverall and reſpective Laws of SCOT<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>LAND and ENGLAND, now alſo in force in SCOTLAND, by the Union of both NATIONS.</head>
            <div type="penalties_by_country">
               <head>By the Laws of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The paines of haueing out Gold, Siluer, Balzeon.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſtatute and ordained,</hi> That na man have out of the Realme, Gold, Siluer, nor Bulzeon, vnder the paine of eſcheateing thereof, the ane halfe thereof to the tani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and taker. <hi>J.</hi> 2. <hi>Par.</hi> 8. C. 34.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of houſeing Wooll, Hide, Skyns.</note>
                  <hi>It is ſtatute and ordained,</hi> for cauſeing of the Cuſtomes to cum in hail, and to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew the defraudeing, that na man houſe VVooll, Hide nor Skynes in <hi>Leith,</hi> nor other places, out-with free Burrowes, vnder the paine of Eſcheit. <hi>J.</hi> 4. <hi>Par.</hi> 6. C. 88.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of carrying out Talloun.</note>
                  <hi>It is ſtatute and ordained,</hi> that na perſon nor perſons take vpon hande in time to cum, to carry ony Talloun foorth of the Realme, vnder the paine of tinſell of all their goods moueable, cumand in contrair hereof. All Cuſtomers to ſearch and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34528:38"/>ſeek all Schippes, and quhair any Talloun beis ſhipped, or brocht to the Shippes to be carried foorth, to eſcheit the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. V. <hi>J. Par.</hi> 5. C. 125.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Huddrouns, Kid-skins.</note>
                  <hi>All Lieges</hi> quhatſumever, are inhibited and diſcharged of all tranſporting and carryeing forth of Huddrounes and Kid-skinnes, vnder paine of confiſcation of the ſame. <hi>J.</hi> VI. <hi>Par.</hi> 12. C. 155.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Na perſon</hi> or perſons is to take vpon hand to tranſport or in-bring any forbidden or uncuſtomed Goods,<note place="margin">Of transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bringing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed guds.</note> vnder paine of tynſell of their Moueable goods, that ſhall happen to come in the contrair thereof; That is to ſay, the ſaids forbidden and uncuſtomed goods that ſhall happen to be taken and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, to be eſcheit, and the remanent of the moueable goods and geare perteining to the Contraueniers, to be eſcheit for their contempt. <hi>J.</hi> VI. <hi>Par.</hi> 16. C. 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of receiueing forbidden or vther guds then ſall be conteyned in the Cocquet.</note>
                  <hi>All Merchants</hi> and Skyppers at the receiving of their Cocquets in all Ports, ſall give their ſolemne eathes, that they haue na forbidden guds, nor na uther lawfull guds or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, except that whilke is conteined in their Cocquet and Entrees, and that they ſall take na uther guds in, all that Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, vnder the paines of hauand the ſhippe arreiſt, and all the guds conteined therein. <hi>J.</hi> VI. <hi>Par.</hi> 15. C. 257.</p>
               <p>In the 15. <hi>Par.</hi> of <hi>James</hi> the VI. C. 251. full Power and Commiſſion was given to his Highneſs Councell, to maike Ordinances neceſſaire for the eaſe of Merchants, and ſuretye of his Highneſs Cuſtomes; And by Act of the Councill <hi>apud Edinb.</hi> the 25. <hi>Oct.</hi> 1611. It was ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ordeined;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of packing guds in packs and trees of gads of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trair nature, or concealeing the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given up in entrie.</note>
                  <hi>That na Merchants</hi> are to take upon hand at any time to pack, or incloſe within Packs of Skinnes, or other Packs tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported forth of this Realme, or within Packs of Lint or Hemp, Trees of Carts, Cardes, or Keames, or other Packs or Trees, any vther Geare or Merchandize of contrair nature, and conceal the ſame ungiven up in Entrie, in defraud of his Highneſſe dew Cuſtoms, vnder pain of eſcheating of the haill Pack ſwa found, wherein the ſame Geare ſall be ſwa found to be fraudfully packed.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34528:38"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Na Maiſters,</hi> Merchants, Awners; nor Skippers of Schips, Crears or other Veſſels, ſall take vpon hand to laiden or loſſe their Schips in haill or in part, at any vnfree Port, or in any open Raids within the ſame, vnder the paine of eſcheating of the haill Merchandize and gudes ſwa ſhipped or loſſed; and of the Schips, Crears and Veſſels wherein the ſamine ſall be ſhipped, and out of the whilke the ſamine ſall be loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Maſter refuſand to make eath. That be hes na forbidden guds, nor na vther geare then whilke is conteyned in his Entry, &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>The Maister,</hi> before his goeing forth, is to make En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Gudes and Merchandize in his Schip, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcryue the ſamen with his hand, and make eath, and with all, ſolemnedly make faith and ſweere, that he hes na for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden gudes nor geare, nor na vther lawfull Merchandize nor gudes within his ſaid Schippe, by and attour that whilke is contained in the ſaid Entryes, ſubſcryved with his hand, nor that he knawes of nane to be brought within the ſaid Schipp, nor ſall not receiue thereafter any gudes or geare to be laidned within his ſaid Schipp; Whilke eath, gif it be refuſed to be made, It ſall be leſome to the Cuſtomer, to arreiſt the ſaid Schipp, and all the gudes and gear being therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">All perſons receiuand guds or geare to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, after vpgiueing their Entries.</note>
                  <hi>Na Maiſters,</hi> Awners nor Skippers of any Schipp paſſing out, are to take vpon hand to receiue within their ſaids Schips and Veſſels, any Merchandize, gudes or geare to be tranſported out of the ſame, after that they haue made and giuen up their Entries to his Highneſs Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, vnder paine of eſcheating the gudes and geare ſa ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and of the Schips, Crears and Veſſels wherein the ſamine ſall be ſhipped.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of loſſing any guds till en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,</note>
                  <hi>Na Maiſter,</hi> Awners nor Skippers of Schips arriuering within this Realme, take vpon hand at any time hereafter, to loſſe any Wines, Merchandize, gudes and geare, vnder whatſomever color or pretence, at any Port or Part, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy any of the ſame away in defraude of the Cuſtomes, vntill ſic time as entrye of their Schips be made;<note place="margin">Or landing guds vngiuen up.</note> and that they leaue noe part of the ſaids Wines, Merchandize, gudes and geare ungiven vp in the ſaid Entry, nor conceale noe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34528:39"/>part thereof from the Cuſtomer, vnder the paine of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheateing of the haill Wynes, Merchandize, gudes and geare ſwa to be loſſed out of the ſaids Schips, and of the Schips, Crears and Veſſels out of the whilke the ſamine ſall be loſſed; As alſo vnder paine of eſcheateing of the haill Merchandize, gudes and geare left out, vngiuen up in the ſaid Entry.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per refuſand to make eath of his Entrie, &amp;c.</note>The Entry to be giuen be the Skipper or Maiſter, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriued with his hand, wha ſall be obleiſt ſolemnedly to make Faith, that the ſame is a juſt and true Entrie of the haill Merchandize and gudes ſhipped within his Schip at that Voiage, and that he has loſſed na part thereof, nor convoyed nane of the ſame away, before the giving up of the ſaid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; Whilke eath, gif it be refuſed to be made, as ſaid is, it ſall be leſome to the ſaids Cuſtomers, to arreiſt the ſaid Schip and haill gudes and Merchandize therein.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Apud</hi> Edinb. <date>
                        <hi>Oct.</hi> 25. 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="penalties_by_country">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:34528:39"/>
               <head>By the Laws of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The penalties of ſhipping out Gold, Silver, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Bullion</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O Perſon</hi> is to carry out any Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in Money, Bullion, Plate, or Veſſel, upon forfeiture of the ſum carried or ſent out. 4. <hi>R.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>Any Searcher finding Gold or Silver in Coyn, or in Maſſe, in the keeping of any that is paſſing, or upon his paſſage in any Ship or Veſſel, to go out of any Port, Haven, or Creek with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Licence, all that Gold or Silver ſhall be forfeit, his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable expences excepted, which he ſhall diſcover preſently, being charged and warned ſo to do by the Searcher, or elſe all the money concealed ſhall be forfeited. 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4.5. The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer and Informer to have the one fourth part of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture. 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p>None ſhall carry or convey any Bullion, Plate, or Coyn of Gold and Silver into <hi>Ireland,</hi> above the ſum of Six ſhillings eight pence, nor convey any ſuch Bullion, Plate, or Coyn into any Ship, Boat, or other Veſſels, upon pain to forfeit the ſame, and to have Impriſonment, and make Fine and Ranſom at pleaſure. 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Braſſe, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Latton, Bell-mettall, Pan-mettall, Gun-mettall Shraffe.</note>
                  <hi>Every Perſon</hi> and Perſons carrying or conveying, or ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to the intent to carry or convey any Braſſe, Copper, Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Bell-metall, Pan-mettall, Gun-mettall, or Shruffe-mettall, whether it be clear or mixed, (Tin, and Lead only excepted) into any part beyond the Seas, forfeits double the value thereof, and Fourty pounds for every Thouſand weight of the ſame. 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8.7. 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.37.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34528:40"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Or carrying the ſame to any part of the Coaſt without Bond</note>
                  <hi>Every perſon</hi> ſhipping or carrying any of the ſaid Mettals, to carry and diſcharge the ſame in any Port of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> unleſſe ſuch perſon, or perſons before the ſhipping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, do declare and manifeſt to the Cuſtomer of the Port where the ſame ſhall be ſhipped, the true weight thereof, and alſo make a ſufficient Obligation in Law, in which he will be bound in ſuch ſum as ſhall amount unto the double value, and Fourty pound for every Thouſand weight ſo declared or manifeſted, with Condition that the ſame ſhould be diſcharged at ſome Port accordingly, and in no other place, doth forfeit as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.37.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer taking Bonds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out date, or making falſe Certificates.</note>Every Cuſtomer by covin or other undue means, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhipping of any the ſaid Mettals contrary hereunto, ſhall permit any perſon to make Obligation without Dates, or making falſe Certificates for diſcharge of their Mettall, looſes his Office, and the value of the Mettall ſo ſhipped. 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8.7. 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.37.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Owner, Purſer, &amp;c. permitting or not diſcloſing the ſhipping ſuch Mettals.</note>Any Maſter, Owner, Purſer, or Boatſwain of any Ship, willingly permitting or ſuffering any ſuch Mettals contrary hereunto, or elſe perceiving any ſuch Mettall to be ſhipped who ſhal not diſcloſe the ſame within three dayes after know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had, to the Cuſtomer of the Port, forfeits double the value of the ſame Mettall. 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.37.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſuffering them to paſſe without ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</note>Every Cuſtomer ſuffering any the Mettals aforeſaid to be ſhipped contrary hereunto, or elſe knowing thereof, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing nevertheleſſe to ſeize the ſame, looſes his Office, and double the value of the ſaid Mettals. 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any</hi> manner of perſon ſhall carry and tranſport by any Ship,<note place="margin">Of ſhipping out Wheat, Rye, Barley, Malt, Corn, Grain Butter, Cheeſe, Wood, without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</note> or other Veſſell, into any parts beyond the Seas, any Wheat, Rye, Barley, or other Corn, or Grain growing in this Commonwealth, or any Malt made within the ſame Butter, Cheeſe, or Wood, without Licence for doing thereof; The Owner, or Owners of the ſaid Ships and Veſſels forfeit the ſame, with their apparell thereunto belonging; The owners of the ſaid Corn, Butter, Cheeſe, and Wood, double the value of the ſame; And the Maſter and Marriners of every the ſaid Ships, for every ſuch offence, forfeit all their Goods,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34528:40"/>and are to be Impriſoned for one year without Bail or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. 1. and 2. <hi>P.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of any carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corn, &amp;c. to any Ship at Sea, or within Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note>If any perſon or perſons ſhall carry and convey by Boat, Crayer, or other Veſſell, any Corn or Grain, Butter, Cheeſe, or Wood, to any Ship or Veſſell on Sea, or within any Haven, Creek or other place, to be tranſported into any Forreign parts; The owners of the Corn, Ships, Veſſels, Boatſ-man and Marriners reſpectively forfeit as aforeſaid. 1. &amp; 2. <hi>P.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of ſuch as ſhal ſhip more then they have Licence for.</note>Any perſon having Licence to tranſport Corn, Victuall, or Wood, ſhall neither himſelf, nor any other unto whom he may aſſign ſuch his Licence, carry out more then is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid Licence upon pain of forfeiting triple the value of what ſhall be tranſported without Licence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Impriſoned in the Common Goal for one whole year, without Bail or Mainprize. 1. &amp; 2. <hi>P.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Or more then at one place.</note>Any perſon having Licence to tranſport Corn; Victuall, and Wood, ſhall not ſhip or lade the ſame, or any part thereof at ſundry, but at one certain place only, upon forfeiture of the ſaid Corn, Victuall, and Wood, and all his Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels. 1. &amp; 2. <hi>P.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> 5. Notwithſtanding all which Corn may be tranſported to any parts not in enmity,<note place="margin">When, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, Corn may be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</note> when the Common price of Corn exceeds not at the place of ſhipping, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <abbr>L.</abbr>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <abbr>S.</abbr>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <abbr>D.</abbr>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Wheat.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>12.</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rye.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>00 <hi>The Quarter.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 4.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peaſe and Beans.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>16.</cell>
                        <cell>00 <hi>The Quarter.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 4.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Barley Malt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                        <cell>16.</cell>
                        <cell>00 <hi>The Quarter.</hi> 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 4.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">And Victuall for proviſion, for Ireland.</note>And any perſon may carry out Victuall for the neceſſary victualling and proviſion of his and their Ships. 1. &amp; 2. <hi>P. M.</hi> 5. for <hi>Ireland,</hi> by Ord. of Parl. 18. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1652.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of ſhipping Yarn.</note>
                  <hi>Every perſon</hi> or perſons ſhipping, carrying, or conveying into any parts beyond the Seas, any Yarn, called Wolſtead Yarn, not made nor wrought in Cloath, and ſpun in the Realm, forfeits Fourty ſhillings for every pound thereof which ſhall be ſo ſhipped, carryed, or conveyed. 33. <hi>H</hi> 8.16. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:34528:41"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Woollen Yarn. Cloth not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought.</note>Any perſon Denizen, or Stranger tranſporting woollen Yarn or Cloath, not fulled nor fully wrought, or not barbed, rowed, and ſhorn, into any parts beyond the Seas, forfeits the value of the ſaid Yarn or Cloath. 7 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.3.3. <hi>H.</hi> 7.11.</p>
               <p>White woollen Cloaths, ſold for Four pounds and under, and coloured Cloath ſold for Three pounds and under excepted. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.13.33. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Cloaths, not to be tranſported un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought, though with Licence, upon forfeiture of Fourty ſhillings for every Cloath. 8. <hi>El.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every perſon,</hi> or perſons ſhipping, lading, carrying, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying any white Aſhes beyond the Seas,<note place="margin">White Aſhes.</note> forfeits Six ſhillings eight pence for every Buſhell of Aſhes ſo ſhipped, laded, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or conveyed. 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No manner</hi> of perſon ſhall tranſport any Horſe, Gelding, or Mare without Licence,<note place="margin">Horſe, Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Mare, unleſſe not exceeding Ten ſhillings price.</note> upon pain of forfeiture not only of every ſuch Horſe, Gelding, or Mare, but alſo Fourty pounds for every of the ſame which ſhall be ſo tranſported. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.13. Nevertheleſſe, any one may carry and ſend beyond Sea any Mares, whereof the price of any one Mare ſo to be carried, doth not exceed Ten ſhillings, in ſuch and like manner as Mares, of the price of Six ſhillings eight pence were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the ſaid Act of Parliament. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.13. Whereby it is required, that ſuch Mares be of the age of three years at leaſt, and that the Seizure at time of ſeizure give the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor the price of Ten ſhillings.<note place="margin">Or ſhall be ſent for Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, or any the Engliſh Plantations of America.</note> 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.5. The ſame may alſo nevertheleſſe be ſent for <hi>Ireland,</hi> by order of Parliament, the 18. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1652. and for any the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>America,</hi> with Licence of his Highneſſe, or Councill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any manner</hi> of perſons bringing, delivering, ſending, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, taking, or procuring to be brought, delivered, ſent, or received into any Ship,<note place="margin">Of ſhipping Rams, Sheep, or Lambs, alive.</note> or Bottom, any Rams, Sheep, or Lambs, or any manner of other kind of Sheep being alive, to be carried into Forreign parts (except ſuch as ſhall be ſent to <hi>Ireland</hi>) doth for the firſt offence, together with his Aiders, Abettors, Procurors, not only forfeit and looſe all his Goods, but is to be Impriſoned for the ſpace of one year, without
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34528:41"/>Bail or Mainprize, and at the expiration thereof, to have his left hand cut off and nailed up in the open Market. 8. <hi>El.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Leather, Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Raw-hides.</note>
                  <hi>Any perſon</hi> or perſons ſhipping, lading, or carrying in any Veſſell, or Ship, any Leather, Tallow, or Raw-hides, with intent to tranſport the ſame beyond the Seas; the owners of the ſame forfeits ſuch Leather, Tallow, or Hides, and triple their value; the owner of the Ships in which they are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, forfeits their Ships, with their whole apparell;<note place="margin">Any Owner, Maſter, or Marriner, diſcovering their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting within three Months to be freed of any penalty.</note> And the Maſters, and Mariners knowing thereof, do forfeit all their Goods and Chattels, and are to ſuffer a years Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without Bail or Mainprize: But if any Owner or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſuch Ship, ſhall within three Moneths next after his knowledge thereof, or after his return from beyond the Seas, make diſcovery of ſuch Leather, Tallow, and Hides tranſported, with their quantity, and quality, and by whom, where, and in what Ship, or Veſſell,<note place="margin">The ſame may be ſent to Ireland.</note> and juſtifie and prove the ſame; then ſuch Owner, Maſter, or Mariner to be free from incurring any penalty. 18. <hi>El.</hi> 9. The ſame nevertheleſſe may be ſent and tranſported for <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant entring Goods of Strangers in the name of Natives.</note> by Order of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of 18. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1652.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Merchant,</hi> or other Perſon, that ſhall Enter the Goods of a Stranger, in the name of an <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or <hi>Scots</hi> man, forfeits, and looſes the Goods ſo Entred, and all his Goods perſonall.<note place="margin">Of the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Wool, woolen Yarn, woollen Flox, wooll Fells, Fullers Earth, Clay, Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co-pipe Clay, or Fullers Earth.</note> 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any perſon</hi> or perſons, lading, or ſhipping in any Ship, Barge, Boat, Veſſel, or otherwiſe, any Wool, of the growth of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, any woollen Yarn, woollen Flox, wool Fells, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Earth, Clay, Tobacco-pipe Clay, or any other Earth, or Clay, which may be uſed in the Art of Fulling, with intent to tranſport the ſame beyond the Seas, or to carry the ſame to any Ship, or other Veſſell whatſoever, to be tranſported, forfeits all ſuch Wools, woollen Yarn, woollen Flox, wool-Fells, Earth, or Clay,<note place="margin">Of the Owners ſhipping or knowing thereof.</note> and Three ſhillings for every pound of the ſame. <hi>Ordinance</hi> 19. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1647.</p>
               <p>The owner, or owners of the Faith or Clay, forfeits alſo Three ſhillings for every pound; the owner of the Ships or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34528:42"/>Veſſells, knowing of ſuch offence, forfeit all their Intereſt in the ſaid Ships, or Veſſels, with all their apparell, or furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to them or any of them, belonging. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Maſter and Mariners knowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note>The Maſter and Mariners knowing of ſuch offence, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits all their Goods and Chattels, and are to be Impriſoned for one whole year, without Bail, or Mainprize. <hi>Ibid</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the ſaid Commodities laid in any place to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note>Any Wool, woollen Yarn, woollen Flox, wool Fells, or any of the ſaid Earth, or Clay, laid in any place whatſoever, with intention to tranſport, or that the ſame ſhould be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported beyond Sea, or with intention to tranſport, or convey, or that the ſame ſhould be tranſported, or conveyed by Sea to any other Port of this Commonwealth, without entring ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Obligation with the Cuſtomer of the Port, for the true delivery thereof at ſome other place of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: Then, and in ſuch caſe, ſuch Wools, woollen Yarn, woollen Flox, wooll Fells, Earth, Clay, and Three ſhillings for every pound weight,<note place="margin">Of Goods pro hibited tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for the Coaſt, without Bond.</note> are forfeited by the owners of the ſame. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like penalty is upon all Goods prohibited tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſhall be ſhipped, without Bond given, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Ordinance of Parl. 16. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1647.</p>
               <p>Any owner of the Land where ſuch Clay or Earth is digged, or gotten,<note place="margin">Of the owner of the Land, knowing of the ſhipping the Clay.</note> being privy unto, or knowing of ſuch tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by any perſon, or perſons, and not diſcovering the ſame unto ſome Juſtice of the Peace, within three Months after, forfeits for every ſuch offence, Five hundred pounds ſterling. Ordinance of Parl. 19. <hi>January,</hi> 1647.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Juſtices not certifying the ſame into the Exchequer.</note>Every Juſtice, to whom ſuch diſcovery ſhall be made, failing to certifie the ſame to the Exchequer within three Moneths following, forfeits for every offence, An hundred pounds ſterling. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Goods brought from <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> in Strangers Bottoms.</note>
                  <hi>All Goods,</hi> of the production, growth, or Manufacture of <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> Imported in any Ships not belonging to the People of this Commonwealth, or Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof, or whereof the Maſter, or Mariners, are not for the moſt part of them of the People of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34528:42"/>are forfeited, together with the Ship, (with all her Tackle, Guns, and Apparell) in which the ſaid Goods or Commodities ſhall be brought in, or Imported.<note place="margin">Of Goods brought from any other then the place of their growth, Manufacture, or uſuall place of ſhipping.</note> Act of Parl. 9. <hi>October.</hi> 1651.</p>
               <p>No Goods are to be brought in any Veſſels of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth from any other place, then the place of their growth, production, or Manifacture, or from thoſe Ports where the ſaid Goods or Commodities can only be, or are, or uſually have been firſt ſhipped for tranſportation, and from no other like places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> under like forfeiture. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Cod-fiſh, Ling, Herring, Pilchard, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Fiſh and Oyl made and cured by Scots, &amp;c. and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Strangers Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</note>
                  <hi>No Cod-fiſh,</hi> Ling, Herring, Pilchard, or any other kind of ſalted Fiſh, uſually fiſhed for, and caught by the People of this Nation, nor any Oyl made of any kind of Fiſh whatſoever, nor any whole Fins, or Whale-bones, ſhall be Imported into this Commonwealth, but only ſuch as ſhall be caught in Veſſels belonging to, and the Fiſh cured, and Oyl, made by the People of this Commonwealth, under like forfeiture. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Cod-fiſh, &amp;c. ſhipped out in ſtrauge Bottoms.</note>No ſort of od, Ling, Herring, Pilchard, or any kinde of ſalted Fiſh, caught and cured by the People of this Nation, ſhall be exported in any other Veſſels, but ſuch as belong to the People of this Commonwealth, and whereof the Maſter and Mariners are for the moſt part of them, of the People of this Commonwealth,<note place="margin">Goods never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe of the Streights or Levant, may be brought from the uſuall Places of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: alſo Eaſt-India Goods. And likeways any goods of the Spaniſh and Portugaz Dominions, from any part of Spain or Portugall.</note> under the ſame Penalty and loſſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>Ibid.</hi> Notwithſtanding which, any the Commodities of the Streights or Levant Sea, may be imported from the uſuall Ports or Places of lading in the Streights or Levant Seas, although the Commodities be not of the growth of the ſaid Places. Eaſt-<hi>India</hi> Commodities alſo may be brought from the uſuall places of lading, to the Southward or Eaſtward of <hi>Cabo, Bona Eſperanza,</hi> though places not of their growth. And likewaves, the People of this Commonwealth, may, in Veſſels to them belonging, whereof the Maſter and Mariners are of the People of this Commonwealth, lade or bring in from any Ports of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> all ſorts of Goods and Commodities, that have come from, or any way belonged to the Plantations or Dominions of any of them reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34528:43"/>as alſo from <hi>Oſtend,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And all ſort of ſilk Wares bought with the product of Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities from <hi>Oſtend, Newport, Rotterdam,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Newport, Rotterdam, Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Amſterdam</hi> Silk or Silk Wares brought thither by Land from <hi>Italy:</hi> Provided the ſame be the proceed of Engliſh Commodities, without incurring any penalty or forfeiture, for, or by reaſon of the ſame. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Fiſh, Victuall, Wares, or things of what kinde or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever, laden or carryed in any Bottome or Veſſell, whereof any Stranger, or Stranger born (unleſſe ſuch as be Denizens, or naturalized) ſhall be Owners, Part-Owners, or Maſters) from one Port or Creek,<note place="margin">Of Goods car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to, and from the Coaſt in ſtrange Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</note> to other Port or Creek of this Commonwealth, are forfeited, together with the Ship carrying the ſame. <hi>Ibid. Et</hi> 5. <hi>El.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">All Goods to be ſhipped and landed in the day light, And at ſome Key or Wharf where there is a Cuſtomer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</note>
                  <hi>No perſon</hi> ſhall lade, or cauſe to be laden into any Ship or Veſſell, any Goods, &amp;c. to be tranſported, or diſcharge, or cauſe to be diſcharged out of any Veſſell, any Wares brought from beyond the Seas, but onely in the day light, <hi>viz.</hi> from the firſt of <hi>March,</hi> to the laſt of <hi>September,</hi> betwixt Sun-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Sun-ſetting; and thence to the firſt of <hi>March</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, between ſeven in the morning, and four in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and upon ſome open Key or Wharf, to be appointed where a Cuſtomer or Searcher is uſually reſident, upon pain of forfeiture of all ſuch Goods, or double the value, 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Maſter and Mariners to lade and diſcharge at no other then the times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforeſaid.</note>
                  <hi>No manner</hi> of perſon ſhall receive or take into any Ship or Veſſell, any Goods or Merchandize to be tranſported beyond the Seas, nor ſhall diſcharge or lay on Land, out of any Ship or Veſſell, any Goods or Merchandize in any other place, or at any other hours, then is before limited, upon pain that the Owners, Maſter, or other Perſon taking charge, or guiding of any ſuch Ship or Veſſell for that Voyage, ſhall looſe and forfeit for every ſuch offence. 100. l. 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Maſter,</hi> Shipper, Purſer, or other perſon taking charge of a Voyage,<note place="margin">No Maſter or Skipper to lade before entry of his Ship.</note> ſhall receive or take into any Ship or other Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, any Goods or Merchandize, &amp;c. to be tranſported be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, before he ſhall have ſignified to the Cuſtomer of the Port where he ladeth, that he intends to lade, and for what place; nor after lading, ſhall depart out of the Port where he ſhall ſo lade, without ſignifying his lading, what
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34528:43"/>Merchants, and other Perſons have lading with him,<note place="margin">Nor depart after lading, before be ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his lading, and anſwer upon oath.</note> or in his Bottom; and further truly to anſwer upon Oath to ſuch Queſtions as ſhall be demanded of him by the Collector, or other Officer, upon pain to forfeit for every default, not truly advertiſing, or anſwering, 100. l. 4. <hi>El.</hi> 11. 1. <hi>El.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No perſon to land goods</note>
                  <hi>No Owner,</hi> Maſter, Purſer, or other perſon taking charge of any Ship, Crayer, Veſſell or Bottom, wherein any Goods or Wares, &amp;c. ſhall be laden and brought from beyond the Seas, ſhall diſcharge into any Lighter or Bottom, and lay on Land, or procure, cauſe, or willingly ſuffer to be diſcharged into any Lighter or Bottom, and to be laid on Land any Goods, VVares or Merchandize whatſoever, before ſuch Owner, Maſter, or other Perſon taking charge of the Ship, Bottom, Veſſell, or Merchants Goods for that Voyage, ſhall have ſignified and declared to the Cuſtomer or other Officer of the Port, Haven or Creek where he arriveth,<note place="margin">Before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hath made his Report, and anſwered upon oath.</note> the Names of every the Merchant or Laders, and ſhall have truly anſwered to ſuch Queſtions and Interrogatories touching ſuch Goods and Merchandize, as ſhall be then laden in any ſuch Ship as ſhall be to him adminiſtred by ſuch Cuſtomer or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, openly in the Cuſtom houſe, upon his or their Oath, if need ſo require, upon pain that every ſuch Maſter or other perſon, ſhall forfeit and looſe for every ſuch default,<note place="margin">All goods to be entred in the names of the Owners.</note> not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advertizing nor anſwering, as is aforeſaid, 100. l. 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No perſon</hi> ſhall take upon him to enter, or cauſe to be entred any Goods or Merchandize coming from, or going into any the parts beyond the Seas, in the name or names of any other perſons, then the very Owner or Owners of the ſame Goods, being not ſold, bargained or contracted for, to, or with any perſon or perſons before ſuch Entry, or before the arrivall of ſuch Goods in the parts beyond the Seas, upon forfeiture of the value of the Goods ſo entred,<note place="margin">No Wharſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Grane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, &amp;c. to contal any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</note> 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Wharſinger,</hi> Crane keeper, Searcher, Lighterman, or other Officer belonging to the Cuſtoms, who ſhall conſent or know of any Offence, contrary to the Act aforeſaid, and do not within one Moneth after his knowledge thereof, diſcloſe the ſame to the chief Cuſtomer, or other Officer of the Port
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34528:44"/>within whoſe Office or Charge any ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, ſhall for every ſuch concealment, forfeit and loſe 100. l. 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Goods uncuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note>
                  <hi>All Merchants,</hi> aſwell Denizens, as others, ſhipping or putting any Goods or Merchandize into any Boat or Veſſell, to the intent to be conveighed beyond the Seas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Parts beyond the Seas, into any Port or Place of this Commonwealth, and unſhipping the ſame, to be ſaid on Land, the Cuſtoms and other Duties not paid, forfeit all ſuch Goods and Merchandize. <hi>Ordin. of Parl,</hi> 21. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1644. 16. <hi>Decem.</hi> 1647.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Certificate to be given for Goods going to the Coaſt.</note>
                  <hi>Every Merchant,</hi> as well Denizen as Stranger, bringing and entring Goods with the Cuſtomers in any Port, and the Duties thereof paid, who will after that, conveigh or carry away the ſame from thence, to any Port within the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Himſelf, Factor or Atturney, ſhall bring from the Cuſtomer of the Port where the Goods were ſo entred, a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate under the Cuſtomers Seal, directed to the Cuſtomer of the Port whereto the ſame ſhall be conveighed or carryed of the naturall colour, length and value uſed to be meaſured with Eln or Yard, as of the naturall weight, content or value of all other Goods uſed to be weighed or valued, to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Cuſtomer before the ſaid Goods be diſcharged, upon pain of forfeiture of the ſame. 3. <hi>H.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Cuſtome or Cheque to uſe trading.</note>
                  <hi>No Cuſtomer,</hi> Comptroller, nor any their Cheques, Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Servants or Factors, ſhall have any Ships of their own, or ſhall buy or fell by way of Merchandize, nor ſhall meddle with fraighting or ſhipping, or have or occupy any Wharf or Key, or hold any Hoſtelry or Tavern, or ſhall be any Factor or Atturney for any Merchant, nor ſhall be Hoſt unto any Merchant, upon pain of forfeiting Fourty pounds, as often as they do the contrary 20. <hi>H.</hi> 6.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Cuſtomer to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Officer or Deputy of ſuch.</note>
                  <hi>No perſon</hi> ſhall take upon him to be Cuſtomer, Compt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roller or Searcher in any Port in any City, Burrough or Town, where he is a common Officer, or Deputy to any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Officer, upon forfeiture for every half year that he occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieth the ſaid Offices, the ſum of Four pounds 3. <hi>H.</hi> 7.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34528:44"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Cuſtomer to conceal or conſent to any thing in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</note>
                  <hi>Every Cuſtomer,</hi> Comptroller, or Searcher, ſhall from time to time, do his or their diligent attendance, at the houſes, times and places appointed, as well in the Cuſtom-houſe or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, as ſhall be moſt for the diſpatch of the Merchant, without concealment or conſenting to any thing which may be to the hurt or damage of his Highneſs, in the juſt anſwering of the Cuſtoms, upon pain that every ſuch Cuſtomer, Compt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roller or Searcher, ſhall forfeit and looſe for every Offence, his or their ſeverall Offices, and an hundred pounds ſterl. 1. <hi>El.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cuſtomer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king falſe Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates of Leather.</note>
                  <hi>Every Cuſtomer</hi> and Officer making falſe Certificate of the arrivall of any Leather in any Port or Creek, ſhall for every ſuch Offence, forfeit one hundred pounds. 1. <hi>Ja.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Or knowing of Leather ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, do not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe ſeize or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the ſame, forfeit <hi>100l.</hi> No Officer to take any fee or gratuity.</note>
                  <hi>Every Cuſtomer,</hi> Comptroller or Searcher, hearing or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Leather, meant to be tranſported, and ſhall not do his beſt to ſeize it; or, being tranſported, ſhall not diſcloſe it, ſhall for his firſt offence, forfeit a hundred pounds, and for the ſecond, his Office. 1. <hi>Ja.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any Officer</hi> of the Cuſtoms, taking or receiving from the Merchant, or any other perſon, any moneys by way of Fee or Gratuity, for any Certificate, Bill or Cocquet, or any other thing whatſoever forfeits his Place. <hi>Collect. of Ordinances as to Cuſtoms. fol</hi> 98.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="penalties">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:34528:45"/>
               <head>By the LAWS made and ordained touching <hi>Excize,</hi> or <hi>New-Impoſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The penalty of Goods landed at unſeaſonable hours.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Maſters</hi> and Commanders of Ships delivering any Goods out of his or their Veſſels or Ships (not being in Wrack or Leak) at any other time but only in day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, that is to ſay, between Sun-riſing and Sun-ſetting, from the firſt of <hi>March</hi> unto the laſt of <hi>September,</hi> and from the laſt of <hi>September</hi> to the firſt of <hi>March</hi> following, between the hours of Seven in the morning, and Five in the afternoon; Or elſe ſuffering or permitting any Goods to be put on board any Lighter,<note place="margin">Or put into any Boat, without conſent of the Waiter on board.</note> Hoy, Boat or other Veſſels, without the conſent or knowledge of the Waiter on board, forfeits One hundred Pounds. <hi>Collection of Acts and Ordinances of Parliament for Excize. Folio</hi> 48.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Every Boat carrying goods from the Ship, to have a Note from the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer on board,</note>
                  <hi>All perſons</hi> into whoſe Boat or Veſſel any Goods paying Excize or Cuſtom imported into any Road, Harbour or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſhall be delivered to carry the ſame on ſhore, is to take from the Officer on board the Ship, out of which the Goods ſhall be delivered, a Note ſpecifying the Name of the Perſon having charge of ſuch Boat or Veſſel, with the Marks and Numbers of every Hogſhead, Cask, Hogſhead-Park, Fardel, Truſſe, Bail, Seron, Bag, Potacco, Ballet, Roll, Bundel, or outward form or bulk of any Parcel or Piece-Goods to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Waiter on ſhore,<note place="margin">To be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on ſhore.</note> appointed to receive the ſame, Upon Forfeiture of his Boat or Veſſel, and of the Goods alſo, if the Owner of the ſame be found guilty of any fraudulent or indirect practice. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 49.50.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:34528:45"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Planter or unknown perſon to take up goods with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out payment of the Excize, or Bond given.</note>
                  <hi>No perſons</hi> living beyond the Seas, nor Planters in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> or <hi>Vèrginia,</hi> or unknown perſons having no certain ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in the Port where any Goods ſhall be entred inwards, are to take up, or receive Warrant for taking up his or their Goods, before payment, or Bond given for payment of the Excize of the ſame, upon pain of Forfeiture of double the value of the ſaid Goods. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 52.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Or enter goods in any other than the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers name.</note>Any ſuch perſon entring Goods in other than the Owners Name, or making uſe of the Name of any known Merchant to colour his Goods, forfeits double the value thereof. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 52.53.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Nor deliver them to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, if be be a Retailer.</note>Any ſuch perſon taking up his Goods by Bond, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering them unto his Security (who is a Retailer of the ſame Commodity) incurs the like Forfeiture; As alſo doth the Security receiving any part of them. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 53.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Shop-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or Retailer to take up Goods without payment of Excize.</note>Any Shop-keeper or Retailer, importing any Commodities or Wares of his own Trade, taking and carrying the ſame away without, or before payment of full Excize of the ſaid Goods, or entring or taking up his Goods in any other perſons Name than his own, forfeits double the value; As doth alſo any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon entring or taking up any Goods for ſuch Shop-keeper or Retailer.<note place="margin">Nor in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name but his own.</note> 
                  <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 54.55.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any Shop-keeper</hi> or Retailor, taking up Goods at ſight, and corrupting the Officer unto whoſe veiw or examination ſuch Goods ſhall be committed,<note place="margin">Penalty of a ſhopkeeper cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, And of the Officer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</note> for obtaining favour in report of his Goods viewed, forfeits double the value of all ſuch Goods; And the Officer ſuffering himſelf to be corrupted, or taking any Reward or ſum of Money, in execution of his Truſt, whereby the Commonwealth may be prejudiced, either in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms or Excize, forfeits One hundred Pounds, and is to be diſmiſſed from his Imployment. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 55.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſhopkeeper is after clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his goods to carry them directly to his own houſe, and not remove the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again without Ticket.</note>
                  <hi>Every Shop keeper</hi> or Retailer after entry and clearing of his Goods is to carry the ſame to his own Shop directly, and is not to houſe the ſame in any other Shop, Celler or Warehouſe, or other place, without firſt acquainting the Commiſſioners, Sub-Commiſſioners, or Collectors therewith; Nor again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ſame (except only from his uſual or known Shop)
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34528:46"/>without a Ticket or Warrant, upon penalty of forfeiture of double the value. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 56.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Goods unduly entred.</note>
                  <hi>All Goods</hi> which, upon opening or ſearch, ſhall be found unduly or fraudulently entred, either for quantity or quality, are forfeited to the Commonwealth. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Penalty of a Wharfinger, &amp;c. taking up or leting down any Goods, but in the preſence of an Officer of the Cuſtoms. No Goods to be landed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out entry.</note>
                  <hi>Any Wharfinger,</hi> or Keeper of any Wharf, Crane, or any Porter taking up, or letting down, or otherwiſe permitting to be brought on ſhore, or ſhipped off any Goods, but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of an Officer of the Cuſtoms, forfeits Five Pounds. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 57.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any Merchant</hi> or Importer, landing, or cauſing any Goods to be landed upon the ſhore, before due entry of the ſame, forfeits double the value of thoſe Goods. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any Merchant</hi> entring Goods in any Port, and afterwards carrying them by Land-carriage to any other Port,<note place="margin">Goods going by Land car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to have Ticket.</note> is not to diſpoſe of ſuch Goods from the Waggon or other Carriage, without firſt delivering his Ticket, or Copy of his firſt Entry, upon pain of forfeiting in like manner, as aforeſaid. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 58.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Merchant to romage without ticket.</note>
                  <hi>The Importer</hi> of any forreign Commodities, removing or romaging the ſame from any place where they were once hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, without a Ticket or Officer, forfeits double the value of the Goods romaged or removed. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Goods cleared or unſold, not to be romaged without ticket,</note>
                  <hi>Every perſon</hi> removing, romaging or carrying from one houſe to another, any Goods or Commodities whatſoever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cizable, though unſold, or that the Excize be already paid, without a Ticket or Officer, forfeits double the value thereof. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 33. Which Ticket is to expreſſe the very quantity of the Goods,<note place="margin">Expreſſing the Deliverer and Receiver.</note> the names of the Deliverer and Receiver, and therefore to be reputed no Warrant or Ticket for Goods to be delivered from, or received by any other then ſhall be nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and deſigned therein.<note place="margin">No Merchant to lodge Goods with a Retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, nor in any other than in his own houſe, celler or ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Importer,</hi> after clearing his Goods at the Cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, houſing or diſpoſing of the ſame in the Houſe, Celler, Warehouſe, Storehouſe, or Shop of any perſon who is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailer of the ſame Commodity, Or houſing or diſpoſing of the ſame in any other Celler, Warehouſe, or Storehouſe, except
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34528:46"/>in his own Houſe or Celler, or Warehouſe thereof, without acquainting the Officers of Excize therewith, forfeits Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pounds. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 58.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Goods ſold to be delivered without ticket</note>
                  <hi>Every Merchant,</hi> after entring and houſing of his Goods, who ſhall ſell and deliver any of his Goods, without receiving a Ticket or Warrant for doing thereof from the Office under which he liveth, forfeits double the value of the ſaid Goods; and every Buyer or other perſon receiving ſuch Goods, incurs like forfeiture. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 58.59.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Merchant to clear his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, and the Buyer to pay his Excize within twenty eight dayes.</note>
                  <hi>Any Merchant</hi> who cannot aſcertain the quantity of his Commodity at the time of the Sale, having obtained a Bill of Sufferance for delivery thereof, is, before the end of Twenty eight dayes, to certifie the perfect weight and meaſure of his Goods ſold, or elſe forfeits double the value: And the Buyer neglecting to pay and fully clear the Excize of thoſe Goods within that time, incurs the like forfeiture. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 59.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Goods import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for private uſe to pay Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize.</note>
                  <hi>Every perſon</hi> importing Commodities excizable for his own private uſe, or for any other purpoſe then to ſell again, is to pay Excize as if the ſame were ſold, or elſe to forfeit double their value. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 61.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Penalty of the Merchant neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt and pay what be ſtands charged with.</note>
                  <hi>Every Merchant</hi> ſummoned to accompt, and after neglect in doing thereof, being warned to pay in the Excize of all ſuch Goods for which he ſtands charged by Entries at the Cuſtom houſe, failing or refuſing to do the ſame within fourteen dayes, forfeits the double value of the ſaid Goods. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 61.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Penalty of any perſon refuſing an Officer to ſearch.</note>
                  <hi>Any perſon</hi> refuſing to permit any Officer, eſpecially autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized thereunto, to enter any Cellers, Warehouſes, Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, or other places,<note place="margin">Of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Officer, who ſhall taſt or view his Tobaccoes: And alſo of the Officer. Of perſons neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to give teſtimony.</note> to ſearch and take accompt of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported Commodities, forfeits Fifty Pounds for every ſuch refuſal. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 62.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any Merchant</hi> Importer, or Buyer of any Wines, or To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baccoes, which ſhall corrupt any Officer appointed to Taſt or View any ſuch Wines or Tobaccoes, forfeits double the value of ſuch Wines and Tobaccoes; And the Officer who taſted or viewed the ſame, One years Salary. <hi>Ibid fol.</hi> 63.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any perſon</hi> ſummoned to give Teſtimony on the behalf of the Commonwealth, neglecting to appear, or elſe appearing,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34528:47"/>and refuſing to take Oath, forfeits Five Pounds. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 75.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Sheriff, or Goalor not receiving, or letting a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner eſcape.</note>
                  <hi>Any Sheriff,</hi> Goalor, or other perſon refuſing to receive into his or their Cuſtody any Perſons committed to them by the Commiſſioners, their Sub-Commiſſioners, or Collectors, or elſe ſuffering them to eſcape or go out of Priſon, without Warrant from thoſe by whom they were committed, forfeits double the value of every ſum of Money for which ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was committed. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 77.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of negligent or remiſſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</note>
                  <hi>Any Officer</hi> wilfully negligent, remiſſe, or refractory, is to be puniſhed at pleaſure of the Commiſſioners, by Fine, not exceeding double the value of his yearly Wages, to be levied, as all other Forfeitures, by Diſtreſſe, or elſe Impriſonment of his Perſon. <hi>Ibid. fol.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſeveral</hi> Officers imployed in the buſineſſe of Cuſtoms and Excize,<note place="margin">Diſpoſition of Fines.</note> are to take notice, That of all Fines and Forfeitures touching or concerning both, or either of them (except where any ſpecial proviſion is made otherwiſe) the one moyetie, or half part, is allowed, and of right belongeth unto the Seizor, Diſcoverer, or other, who ſeizes, makes or brings Information of the breach of any the Laws of Cuſtoms or Excize; and the other moyetie, or half part, unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:34528:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
